<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
		  xml:id="gettingstarted">
	<title>Getting Started Tutorial</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>In this tutorial, we will create and save a simple 
		card, load QSOs from an ADIF file and select the QSOs to 
		print, and finally, print the QSOs.</para>
		<para>The first steps are to become familiar with
		the <link linkend="splashscreen">HamQSLer splash screen
		</link>, become familiar with the 
		<link linkend="mainprogramwindow">main program window,</link>
		and then <link linkend="setfewuserprefs">set a few user 
		preferences</link>.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="splashscreen">
		<title>The HamQSLer Splash Screen</title>
		<para>When <literal>HamQSLer</literal> starts, it performs a number
		of functions:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact' numeration="arabic">
			<listitem>
				<para>Displays the splash screen;</para>
				</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Performs a number of initialization steps
			including initializing the <literal>HamQSLer</literal> directory and its
			contents, creating the user preferences if it doesn't 
			exist, and checking if a new version of the program or
			data files are available.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Destroys the splash screen and displays the main
				program window.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>The first time that you execute <literal>HamQSLer</literal>, the splash
		screen will look similar to this:</para>
		<figure xml:id="firstsplashscreen">
			<title>Splash Screen First Time HamQSLer Started</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/firstsplashscreen.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>There may be one or more additional messages, but as long
		as the Continue button is displayed you may click that to
		continue on to see what the <link linkend="mainprogramwindow">
		<emphasis role='underline'>main program window</emphasis></link> looks like.</para>
		<para>If only a Terminate button is visible, a non-recoverable
		error has occurred and this must be corrected before you can
		go any further. If you cannot determine the cause or solution
		of the problem from the messages displayed on the splash
		screen, see the <link linkend="programinit">
		<emphasis role='underline'>Program Initialization and the Splash 
		Screen</emphasis></link> chapter.</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="mainprogramwindow">
		<title>HamQSLer Main Program Window</title>
		<para>After you click the Continue button on the splash screen,
		the splash screen disappears, and the main program window,
		shown below, is	displayed.</para>
		<figure xml:id="mainwindow">
			<title>Main Program Window</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/mainwindow.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The first time that you start <literal>HamQSLer</literal>, only the QSOs 
		function tab
		will be shown. After you have created one or more cards, and
		depending on certain user preferences, there may be an additional
		tab for each card the next time that you start the program.</para>
		<para>The function tabs select the view that is displayed in 
		the Work Area. The QSOs tab shows the loaded QSOs for which 
		cards may be printed. The QSOs panel, shown in the image below, 
		contains 6 QSOs that have been loaded from an ADIF file, the 
		Sort Cards Panel, and the QSOs filters tabs. The Sort Cards 
		Panel allows you to sort the cards by date and time, by callsign, 
		or by a 
		combination of QSL bureau and manager or callsign. There are
		four QSOs filters tab, each of which contain filters
		for selecting QSOs. The four filters are:</para>
		<itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>mode</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>band</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>date and time</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>QSL statuses</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<figure xml:id="qsospanel">
			<title>QSOs Panel</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/qsos.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The image below shows the card design panel and card
		properties panel. The image shows the design panel immediately
		after a new card has been created. Note the tab label of
		"New Card" and the window title contains this text as well.
		This label and window title change to the name of the card file
		when the card is saved. The X button on the tab can be used
		to close the tab.</para>
		<figure xml:id="cardpanel">
			<title>Card Panel</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/cardpanel.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>With no card item (text, background or other image,
		or the QSOs Box) selected, the properties panel contains default
		print properties for the card. The image above shows this. We
		will discuss printing and this panel later in this tutorial.
		When a card item is selected, the properties
		panel changes to show the properties for that card item. </para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="setfewuserprefs">
		<title>Setting a Few User Preferences</title>
		<para>Now that you are familiar with the main program window,
		we will start to create a sample QSL card. But before we begin
		with the actual design of the card, we must first set a few
		user preferences.</para>
		<para>Select the User Preferences... menu item from the Edit
		dropdown menu. This will display the User Preferences dialog
		shown in the image below.</para>
		<figure xml:id="userprefsdialog">
			<title>User Preferences Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/userprefsdialog.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<section>
			<title>Select the Default Text Font</title>
			<para>Click on the triangle to the left of "TextItems", or
			double-click on the "TextItems" text 
			to open the expander. Now click on "Default Text Font" to
			display the Default Text Font panel.
			See the image below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="defaulttextfont">
				<title>Default Text Font Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaulttextfont.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The dropdown list contains a list of every font that
			is registered on your computer. Select the font that you
			want as the default font for all text items. Don't worry,
			the font can be set individually for each text item when you
			design your card. Sample text in the selected font face is
			shown in the text block below the dropdown.</para>
			<para>You can click on the Apply button to save this change,
			or wait until you have made additional changes before applying
			them.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Set Your Default Callsign</title>
			<para>Click on "Callsign Text" under the TextItems
			expander to display the Callsign Text item panel. There is a
			text editing field that contains the text "MyCall".
			Change "MyCall" to the callsign that you most often use. Do
			not click the Macros button; we will discuss this later when
			we look at the salutation.</para>
			<para>The image below shows what you should see at this point,
			replacing VA3HJ with your callsign.
			</para>
			<figure xml:id="defaultcallsign">
				<title>Default Callsign Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultcallsign.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Either click on the Apply button to save this change,
			or wait until more changes have been made.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Set Your Name and QTH</title>
			<para>Click on "Name and QTH Text" under the Text Items
			expander to display the Name and QTH item panel. The
			panel contains a text editing field containing the text
			"MyQth". Change this text to your name and mailing
			address, using the Return key at the end of all except the
			last line. Again, do not click the Macros button.</para>
			<para>The image below shows what you would see at this
			point if you had entered my name and address.</para>
			<figure xml:id="defaultnameQth">
				<title>Default Name and QTH Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultnameQth.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<tip>
				<para>See 
				<link linkend='nonkeyboardchars'><emphasis role='underline'>Appendix C</emphasis></link>
				if you want to enter characters that are not available
				on your keyboard.</para>
			</tip>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Set Salutation</title>
			<para>Click on the "Salutation Text" item under the TextItems
			expander to display the Salutation panel. This panel contains
			only the Macros button. Click on this button to open the 
			Text and Macros dialog. The dialog should
			look like this:</para>
			<figure xml:id="defaultsalutation">
				<title>Default Salutation Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultsalutation.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The first Static Text groupbox contains
			an edit box with the text "Thanks for the QSO" in it. The 
			Static Text groupbox at the bottom of the dialog similarly 
			contains an edit box with the text ". 73," in it. The
			groupbox in the middle, labeled "Count Macro", contains fields for
			editing the content of a CountMacro. Macros are beyond the
			scope of this tutorial; the CountMacro is simply mentioned
			here because we will discuss it later while we design
			a sample card. Click the Close button to close the dialog.</para>
			<para>Macros are discussed in the 
			<link linkend="macros"><emphasis role='underline'>Macros</emphasis></link>
			chapter.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Select the Default QSOs Box Font</title>
			<para>Open the QSOs Box expander and click on the "Default
			QSOs Box Font" text to open the Default QSOs Box Font
			panel. This panel is similar to the Default Text Font panel.
			Select the font to display QSO information in; this font
			may be the same or different than the default text font.</para>
			<para>All user preferences are discussed in the 
			<link linkend="settinguserprefs"><emphasis role='underline'>Setting
			User Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter.</para>
			<para>Click on the OK button to save the changes and to close
			the dialog.</para>
			<para>Now that we have set a number of user preferences, it
			is time to design your first card.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Designing Your First Card</title>
		<section>
			<title>Creating a Default Card</title>
			<para>To create a card, click on the 
			<guimenu>Cards</guimenu> dropdown
			menu. Click on <guisubmenu>New</guisubmenu>, and then 
			<guimenuitem>Bureau Card</guimenuitem>. Note that you
			can also just type 
				<keycombo action="simul">
					<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
					<keycap>N</keycap>
				</keycombo>.
			</para>
			<para>The image below shows the main window when you have
			performed this action. Note that the properties panel contains
			Default Printer Properties and Default Print Properties.
			</para>
			<figure xml:id="newcard">
				<title>New Card When First Created</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/newcard.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Selecting and Deselecting Card Items</title>
			<para>Move the mouse cursor over the card and the various
			text items and QSOs Box. Each item in turn is surrounded
			by an orange dashed rectangle. This indicates the card item
			that can be selected. With the mouse cursor over the card and
			not one of the text items or Qsos Box, click the 
			<keycombo action="click">
				<mousebutton>right mouse button</mousebutton>
			</keycombo> 
			to display the card context menu.</para>
			<figure xml:id="selectcontextmenu">
				<title>Select Context Menu</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/selectcontextmenu.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The image above shows the context menu that is displayed.
			Click on the 
				<guimenuitem>Select Highlighted Item</guimenuitem>
			menu item.
			The orange dashed rectangle changes to a blue dashed rectangle
			to indicate that the card (actually the Background Image) 
			item is selected, and the properties
			panel changes to contain the properties associated with the
			Background Image.</para>
			<para>Now click the 
				<keycombo action="click">
					<mousebutton>right mouse button</mousebutton>
				</keycombo>
			with the mouse cursor anywhere within the card design panel,
			even outside the card to redisplay the Select Context Menu.
			Click on the 
			<guimenuitem>Deselect Selected Item</guimenuitem> menu item to deselect
			the selected card item.</para>
			<para>Card items may also be selected and deselected using
			the <guimenu>Select</guimenu> dropdown menu. The menu
			contains a menu item for each card item on the card; for 
			any	Image items that have been added for which a filename has
			been specified, there is a menu item that
			contains the name of the image file, and for Image items for
			which a filename has not been specified, 
			the menu items are labeled "Image". 
			The menu items for text items are labeled with the
			first ten characters of the text. There is also a menu item
			with the label "Qsos Box" to allow selection of the Qsos
			Box.</para>
			<para>The final menu item in the Select dropdown menu,
			labeled "None" is used to deselect the selected card item.</para>
			<para>The image below shows the Select dropdown menu for
			the card in its current state. The labels for the callsign
			and name and QTH menu items will match the first ten
			letters of the callsign and name and QTH field that you set
			in the user preferences earlier.</para>
			<figure xml:id="selectmenu">
				<title>Select Dropdown Menu</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/selectmenu.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Setting the Background Image</title>
			<para>Select the background using either the Select context
			menu or the Select dropdown menu. The card will be surrounded
			by a blue dashed line indicating that it is selected, and
			the properties panel will contain the background image
			properties panel, shown in the image below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="backgroundimageproperties">
				<title>Background Image Properties</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/backgroundimageproperties.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Click on the button labeled "..." to open the file
			open dialog, shown below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="fileopendialog">
				<title>File Open Dialog</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/fileopendialog.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The dialog opens in the <filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename>
			directory in your
			documents directory (<filename class='directory'>My Documents</filename>). 
			The actual directory
			is determined by a user preferences setting; see the 
			<link linkend="settinguserprefs"><emphasis role='underline'>User 
			Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter for more 
			information.</para>
			<para>Navigate to the <filename role='directory'>Samples</filename> directory 
			and select the <filename>sample.jpg</filename>
			file. The program's main window will now look
			like this:</para>
			<figure xml:id="backgroundimageoncard">
				<title>Main Window With Background Image Added to Card</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/backgroundimageoncard.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Note the selection rectangle has now extended above 
			and below the top and bottom of the card. The rectangle
			now outlines the edges of the background image, which does
			not have the same aspect ratio as the card. Also, in
			the background image properties panel, the location of the
			image file is shown below the "..." button.</para>
			<para>Move the mouse cursor over the background image. The
			cursor changes to 
			<inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/movecursor.png" valign="middle" />
				</imageobject>
			</inlinemediaobject>
			unless
			you are using a custom set of mouse cursors. This is the
			move cursor. Press and hold the left mouse button and drag
			the mouse around the screen to move background image.</para>
			<para>To change the size of the image, release the
			mouse button, then move the mouse cursor to one of the four
			corners of the image. The cursor will change to either
			<inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/nwse.png" valign="middle" />
				</imageobject>
			</inlinemediaobject>
			or
			<inlinemediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/nesw.png" valign="middle" />
				</imageobject>
			</inlinemediaobject>
			to indicate
			that you are over the corner of the image. Press and hold
			the left mouse button, then drag the cursor away from the
			centre of the image to increase the size of the image, and
			drag the cursor towards the centre of the image to decrease
			the size of the image.</para>
			<para>It is difficult to return the image to its original
			size and position. A simpler way to do this is to reload
			the image. Do so now.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Setting Text Items</title>
			<para>Deselect the background image using either the
			context menu or Select dropdown menu. Select the callsign
			text item. The text item properties panel, shown below,
			 will now be displayed in the properties panel.</para>
			<figure xml:id="textitemproperties">
				<title>Text Item Properties Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/textitemproperties.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>There are a number of properties related to text items;
			we will look at each of them in turn.</para>
			<para>The font dropdown box contains all of the fonts registered
			with your operating system. The font that is currently
			selected is the font that you selected in the user
			preferences earlier in this tutorial. Select a different
			font. The callsign on the card is now displayed in that
			font. Notice that only this text changed font, not the other
			text items.</para>
			<para>The text may be displayed in Bold or Normal 
			weight by checking or unchecking the Bold checkbutton.
			Italic or Normal style may be selected by checking and 
			unchecking the
			Italic checkbutton. Try this. For the callsign
			text, the default is normal style and Bold.</para>
			<para>The size dropdown box contains a number of predefined
			font sizes (in points). 48 is the default value for callsigns.
			You can select any of the sizes
			directly from the list, or edit the size box to enter any
			size that you want. Try entering a character other than
			a number, ".", or ",". Note the beep emitted by your computer to
			indicate that you entered an invalid character. Now select 
			the font size that you want.</para>
			<para>The color button (the button with the black rectangle)
			shows the color that the text is displayed in. Click on this
			button to open the color picker dialog, shown below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="colorpicker">
				<title>Color Picker Dialog</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/colorpicker.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
			The color picker lets you set a color in a number of
			different ways. For example, you can select one of the basic
			or custom colors shown in swatches on the left side of the
			dialog, or you can select a custom color by clicking in the
			rainbow on the right side of the dialog and then adjusting
			the slider to the right of the rainbow to adjust the luminance
			value. Alternatively you may enter hue, saturation and luminance
			values or red, green and blue values in the entry boxes below
			the rainbow. To save as a custom color for later use in the
			program, click on the "Add to Custom Colors" button.</para>
			<para>For this tutorial, a bright orange works best. Set
			red to 255, green to 128, and blue to 0. Save this as a
			custom color because we will be using it again, then click 
			the OK button.
			This closes the color picker dialog. The button in the 
			text item properties panel now displays an orange rectangle,
			and the callsign text on the card is displayed in orange.</para>
			<para>The group box labeled Text holds an edit box containing
			the text of the callsign. Make some changes to the text and
			note that the changes are immediately reflected on the card.
			Reset the text to your callsign.</para>
			<para>Ignore the "Macros" button for now.</para>
			<para>The Checkboxes group box contains four controls, a
			checkbutton for adding a checkbox in front of the text,
			a checkbutton for adding a checkbox after the text, a slider
			for adjusting the thickness of the lines making up the checkboxes,
			and a slider to set the size of the checkboxes as a percentage
			of the height of the text. Adjust each of these controls to see the effect
			they have. The line thickness and check box ratio sliders only
			have an effect when at least
			one of the checkbuttons is checked. Note that the checkboxes
			are displayed in the same color as the text. Uncheck both
			checkbuttons.</para>
			<para>Move the mouse cursor over the callsign text on the
			card. The mouse cursor will change to the move cursor. Press
			and hold the left mouse button, and drag the text to be near
			the top left corner of the card, then release the mouse 
			button.</para>
			<para>Deselect the callsign text and select the text with
			your name and QTH. Change the color of the text to the same
			orange color as the callsign. Adjust the position of the
			text so that the top of the top line of the text is in
			line with the top of the callsign text. Position the text
			so that it is to the right of the callsign. Deselect the 
			text item.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>See 
				<link linkend='nonkeyboardchars'><emphasis role='underline'>Appendix C</emphasis></link>
				if you want to enter characters that are not available
				on your keyboard.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>Now look at the salutation text on the card. Note
			the text is "Thanks for the QSO$. 73, ". The "$" character
			is a placeholder for a Count Macro. We will look at this
			macro in a moment.</para>
			<para>Select the salutation text item. In the text item
			properties panel, note that Text group box contains only 
			a Macros button. Click on this
			button to open the Text and Macros dialog.</para>
			<para>The Text and Macros dialog will contain three main group boxes:
			the groupbox at the top of the dialog, labelled "Static Text",
			contains a text edit box with the text "Thanks for the QSO",
			The second main group box, labelled "Count Macro" will be discussed
			in a moment. The third main group box located at the bottom of
			the dialog is labelled "Static Text" and contains a text edit
			box with the text ". 73," in it. The dialog will look like 
			the image below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="salutationtextandmacros">
				<title>Salutation Text and Macro Dialog (Expanded)</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/salutationtextandmacros.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			
			
			<para>The Count Macro group box
			contains controls for the contents of a Count Macro. A Count
			Macro displays text based on the number of QSOs rows that
			are printed in the QSOs Box for cards with no QSOs, and 
			the number of QSOs printed for cards with QSOs. This count 
			macro is set up to print "s" when the QSOs count is greater
			than one, print nothing when the QSOs count is 1, and to
			display
			"$" on the card in design mode. Each of these values, and
			the condition may be modified. See the 
			<link linkend="macros"><emphasis role='underline'>Macros</emphasis></link>
			chapter for
			more information. We will not make any changes to the
			count macro or its text in this tutorial, so click the Close button to
			close the dialog.</para>
			<para>Change the color of the text to the same orange color
			as the other text items, and make any adjustments to the
			position of the text that you would like. Deselect the salutation
			text item.</para>
			<para>Your card should now look like this:</para>
			<figure xml:id="cardaftertextitemschanged">
				<title>Card After Text Items Edited</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/cardaftertextitemschanged.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Setting Qsos Box Properties</title>
			<para>Deselect any selected card item, then select the Qsos Box.
			The Qsos Box properties panel will be displayed in the properties
			panel. See the image below for a view of the Qsos Box properties 
			panel. The panel contains many properties, and does not fit
			fully in the HamQSLer window. The
			scrollbar to the right of the panel may be used to scroll down
			to the remaining properties, or you may increase the height of
			the program's window to show all of the properties.</para>
			<figure xml:id="qsosboxprops">
				<title>Qsos Box Properties Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/qsosboxprops.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The text that is displayed in the Qsos Box (e.g. the
			confirming text (in the top line of the box, the text for
			each column header, and the text that is displayed in the 
			QSL column, not yet shown on the card) is determined by 
			user preferences and is fixed when the card is first created.
			See the <link linkend="settinguserprefs"><emphasis role='underline'>User 
			Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter for details on setting these
			values.</para>
			<section>
				<title>Setting QSOs and Fields Properties</title>
				<para>Let's look at each property. The Show Manager checkbox
				when checked adds the text "via ZZZZZZ" to the confirmation
				line in design mode, and will replace "ZZZZZZ" with the
				other station's QSL manager if one exists and is included
				in the Manager column of the QSOs printed on the card. We
				will look at this later when we select the QSOs to be printed.
				If no manager exists, the text, including "via" is not
				printed. Check this checkbox as we will be using it later.</para>
				<para>Below the Show Manager checkbox are two radio buttons,
				one labeled "Show Band Column" and the other labeled 
				"Show Freq Column". When
				you create a card, the "Show Band Column" radio button 
				is selected by
				default. These two radio buttons determine whether the 
				Qsos Box displays a band column or a frequency column. Click
				the "Show Freq Column" button. 
				Note that the Band column header
				has changed to "MHz" and that the size of the various columns
				have adjusted themselves.</para>
				<para>What happens if you select the Band radio button but
				your logging program only logs frequency? When the ADIF file
				containing the QSOs is loaded, or when you manually input
				QSOs, a band field will be generated
				for each QSO, with the band corresponding to the band
				containing the logged frequency.</para>
				<para>And what happens if you select the Frequency radio
				button but the QSO only has a band field and not a frequency
				field? When each card is printed, a default frequency for
				that band is substituted. The default frequency for each
				band may be set in the user preferences.</para>
				<para>Make sure that the "Show Band Column" radio button 
				is selected.</para>
				<para>The QSL Pse/Tnx checkbox controls the visibility of
				the QSL column in the Qsos Box. When a card is first created,
				this checkbox is checked. Uncheck the checkbox; note that
				the column labeled "QSL" at the left of the
				Qsos Box has been removed, and the other columns have been 
				resized. The values
				printed in this column depend on the value of the QSL_RCVD
				ADIF field for each QSO. If the field contains "Y" indicating
				that a QSL card has been received confirming this QSO, then
				the text "Tnx" is printed in the column for that QSO. If
				the column contains any other value, the text "Pse" is printed
				in the column. "Tnx" and "Pse" are default values; they may
				be changed in user preferences.</para>
				<para>Make sure that the checkbox is checked before continuing
				with this tutorial.</para>
				<para>The Date Format dropdown box contains three values:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
					<listitem>
						<para>YYYY-MM-DD</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>DD-MMM-YY</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>DD-MM-YY</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>The value selected determines both the text that is
				displayed in the date column header, and the format of the date printed
				for each QSO. Change to a different value to see the effect on
				the Qsos Box. Finally, set this value to YYYY-MM-DD for this
				tutorial.</para>
				<para>The Max Qsos control specifies the maximum number of
				QSOs that may be printed on the card. The control is a
				dropdown box; you may select any value between
				1 and 15. Try multiple values to see how the Qsos Box changes.
				</para>
				<para>The default value when you create a new card is 4.
				There is no way to change this default.</para>
				<para>Finally, set this value to 2.</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Setting Line and Text Properties</title>
				<para>There are three color buttons. Each button opens the
				color picker dialog to allow you to select a color. The three
				colors control the color of the lines and text in the Qsos
				Box, the color of the callsign in the confirming text, and
				the color of the manager in the confirming text. Set the
				line and text color to orange (red=255, green=128, blue=0),
				and set the manager color to green (red=0, green=255,
				blue=0).</para>
				<para>The Font Size dropdown box contains values between
				5.0 and 9.0. This sets the size of the font in the QSOs
				Box. Try different values. For the 2 QSOs that we have set
				as the maximum, a value of 9.0 points is good. Smaller 
				values will
				be needed when you select a large Max QSOs value; otherwise
				the box would not fit on the card.</para>
				<para>The Font dropdown box allows you to select the font
				that the text in the Qsos Box is displayed and printed in.
				The initial font selected in the dropdown box is the font
				that you specified as the default Qsos Box font in the
				User Preferences earlier.
				Select a few different fonts and notice how the height of
				the Qsos Box changes. The actual height of a line of text
				in each font will be different, even though the font size
				has not changed.</para>
				<para>Set the font to a value that looks good to you.</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Setting Qsos Box Background Properties</title>
				<para>These properties control the color and the opacity
				(opposite of transparency) of the background of the Qsos
				Box.</para>
				<para>Click on the Color button to display the color picker
				dialog. This dialog may be used to change the color of the
				background of the Qsos Box. Note that the background color
				of the QSOs Box is now your selected color.</para>
				<para>The opacity slider adjusts the opacity 
				of the background. Adjust the slider to
				select values between 0 and 100% to see the effect on the
				Qsos Box.</para>
				<para>When you have finished playing, set the color to black
				(red=0, green=0, blue=0), and set the opacity to 30%. Note
				that a considerable amount of the detail in the 
				background image shows through.</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Adjusting the Position of the Qsos Box</title>
				<para>Move the mouse cursor over the Qsos Box. The cursor
				will change to 
				<inlinemediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/movecursor.png" valign="middle" />
					</imageobject>
				</inlinemediaobject>
				. Press the left mouse button
				and drag the Qsos Box. When you are done, release the mouse
				button. For this card, positioning the Qsos Box anywhere that
				is not over a text item will work.</para>
				<para>Move the mouse cursor over the left or right edge of
				the QSOs Box. The cursor will change to
				<inlinemediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/ewcursor.png" valign="middle" />
					</imageobject>
				</inlinemediaobject>
				. This indicates that you can move that edge of the QSOs Box either
				left or right to change the width of the box. As you shrink the width
				of the QSOs Box, it will reach its minimum width based on the columns
				and font size selected, and will not shrink any more. The minimum width
				is determined by the width required to print the contents of all
				columns without the contents overlapping to other columns.</para>
				<para>Resize the QSOs Box to approximately the width it was before.
				Deselect the Qsos Box. Your card should look similar
				to the image below:</para>
				<figure xml:id="samplecard">
					<title>Card After Design Complete</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/samplecard.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Saving the Card</title>
				<para>Select the Save Card As... menu item from the Cards
				dropdown menu. This opens the File Save dialog, shown
				in the image below:</para>
				<figure xml:id="savecarddialog">
					<title>Save Card Dialog</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/savecarddialog.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>Note that the dialog opens in the 
				<filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename>
				directory.
				Select the <filename class='directory'>Samples</filename>
				directory; enter the file name
				<filename>sample</filename> in the Name edit box near the top of the dialog,
				and click the Save button. The card will be saved with
				the name <filename>sample.xq1</filename>.</para>
				<para>The text on the tab in the main window will
				change from "New Card*" to "sample.xq1".</para>
				<para>In the future, this card may be opened using the
				Open Card... menu item in the Cards dropdown menu.</para>
				<para>We are now done designing the card, so let's load
				an ADIF file containing some QSOs to select for printing.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Selecting QSOs to Print on the Card</title>
		<para>Click on the QSOs tab. Select Import QSOs... from the 
		QSOs dropdown menu. This opens the File Open dialog in the
		<filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename> directory. 
		Select the <filename class='directory'>Samples</filename> directory, and open
		the file <filename>sample.adi</filename>. The program main window should look
		like this:</para>
		<figure xml:id="sampleqsosloaded">
			<title>Sample QSOs Loaded</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/sampleqsosloaded.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<section>
			<title>Selecting QSOs Sort Order</title>
			<para>The QSOs properties panel is shown below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="qsospropspanel">
				<title>QSOS Properties Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/qsospropspanel.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>As noted here, when an ADIF file is first imported,
			the QSOs are sorted by date and time. QSOs may also be sorted
			by manager and callsign, and by bureau followed by manager
			and callsign. Select each of the sort order radio buttons
			and note how the order of the QSOs changes in the QSOs panel.</para>
			<para>With the Bureau radio button set, note that all QSOs
			with the Send Via column set to "Bureau" are sorted to the
			top of the QSOs panel, followed by QSOs whose Send Via is
			set to Direct. The values in the Send Via column are set 
			according to the values of the QSL_SENT_VIA field in ADIF
			records as follows:</para>
			<table frame='all'>
				<title>Send Via Column Values</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='center' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='QSL_SENT_VIA' colwidth='100 pt'/>
					<colspec colname='Send Via Value' colwidth='100 pt'/>
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='QSL_SENT_VIA'>QSL_SENT_VIA</entry>
						<entry namest='Send Via Value'>Send Via Value</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>B</entry>
							<entry>Bureau</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>D</entry>
							<entry>Direct</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>E</entry>
							<entry>Electronic</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>M</entry>
							<entry>Manager</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry />
							<entry>Bureau</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Any other value</entry>
							<entry>Bureau</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<para>Even though some QSOs may have a value of Electronic
			or Manager in the Send Via column, it is still possible to
			include these QSOs on cards that you print.</para>
			<para>Leave the Bureau radio button selected.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Selecting QSOs by Band</title>
			<para>Note that the checkboxes in the Include column for
			all QSOs are checked to indicate that all QSOs will be
			printed on cards.</para>
			<para>In the QSOs properties panel, click on the Band tab.
			The expanded widget looks like this:</para>
			<figure xml:id="bandproperties">
				<title>Band Properties</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/bandproperties.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Uncheck the 40m checkbox. Note that the checkbox in
			the Include column of the third QSO is now
			unchecked; this is the only QSO that took place
			on the 40m band.</para>
			<para>Leave this unchecked.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Selecting QSOs by Mode</title>
			<para>Click on the Mode tab; it looks like
			the image below. Note that the list contains submode values from the
			QSOs, and only contains a mode value if the QSO does not have a submode
			field.</para>
			<figure xml:id="modeproperties">
				<title>Mode Properties</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/modeproperties.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			
			<para>Uncheck the CW checkbox. All QSOs in the CW mode are
			deselected. Reselect the CW mode checkbox. Again all QSOs
			except the QSO on 40m are selected.</para>
			<para>Leave all modes checked.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Selecting QSOs by Date and Time</title>
			<para>Click on the Date/Time tab. The tab contents
			look like this:</para>
			<figure xml:id="datetimeproperties">
				<title>Date/Time Properties</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/datetimeproperties.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The start date and time fields contain the date and
			time of the earliest QSO in the QSOs panel. The end date
			and time correspond to the date and time of the latest QSO.
			Change the start date to "20021201". Note that the QSOs whose
			start date occur before this date are now unchecked. Similarly, 
			you could change
			the start time and the end date and time to uncheck other
			QSOs.</para>
			<para>Now click the Reset button. The start and end dates
			are reset to the dates and times of the earliest and latest
			QSOs.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Selecting QSOs by QSL Statuses</title>
			<para>The image below shows the content of the QSL Status tab.
			It contains three sections, one for Rcvd statuses, one for
			Sent statuses, and one for Sent Via statuses. </para>
			<figure xml:id="qslstatusproperties">
				<title>Expanded QSL Status Properties</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/qslstatusproperties.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Select various statuses to see the QSOs that are selected
			and deselected. When you are finished, make sure that all
			checkboxes are checked.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Selecting Individual QSOs</title>
			<para>You may select individual QSOs by checking and unchecking
			the checkboxes in the Include column. To do this, you must
			click on the checkbox itself. If you click
			anywhere else on the QSO, the QSO is selected. this is not what
			you want at this time.</para>
			<para>It is also possible to check and uncheck all QSOs at
			once or multiple QSOs at a time. That is covered in the 
			chapter titled 
			<link linkend="workingwithqsos"><emphasis role='underline'>Working
			With QSOs</emphasis></link>.</para>
			<para>Before proceeding, make sure that only the third QSO
			is unchecked.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Printing the Cards</title>
		<section>
			<title>Default Printer and Print Options Properties</title>
			<para>Click on the tab labeled "sample.xq1" to redisplay the
			card that you designed earlier.</para>
			<para>With no card items selected, the card properties panel
			contains printer properties and print properties. The default
			values are the values that are set in User Preferences. Because
			we did not change these values earlier, the printer is set
			to the computer system's default printer. The paper size,
			quality, and paper source are set to the default values
			for this printer.</para>
			<para>The print properties are also set to the defaults set in
			User Preferences. These values control how the cards are printed.
			If the "Print Inside Printer Margins" checkbox is checked and
			disabled, and the "Set Card Margins to Printer Margins" checkbox
			is unchecked and disabled, then the minimum printer margins for
			the selected printer has one or more margins that exceeds ¼ inch
			or 6.35 mm. Printer margins and the reasons for forcing printing
			inside the printer margins are discussed in the 
			<link linkend="outputtingcards"><emphasis role='underline'>Outputting 
			Cards</emphasis></link> chapter</para>
			<para>There are two checkboxes that affect the card in display mode as
			well as print mode:</para>
			<itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
				<listitem>
					<para>"Print Card Outlines" checkbox determines whether a black line
					is drawn around the outside of the card. This helps to determine
					where the card edges are when you cut the cards out of the
					cardstock. Check this box; note that a line is drawn around
					the card in the Card Design Panel.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>"Set Card Margins to Printer Margins" checkbox determines
					whether card contents are printed with a margin inside the card
					edges or card contents are printed to the edges of each card.
					If you select a card layout on your cardstock such that one or
					more cards abut the edges of the cardstock, then the edges of
					those cards abutting the cardstock edges will have a margin
					on them when printed. This occurs because printers do not normally print
					to the edges of paper. In order to look better, checking the Set Card
					Margins to Printer Margins checkbox will provide a margin
					around all edges of every card equal to the widest minimum
					margin for your printer. Check this checkbox now if the checkbox
					is not disabled. Notice that
					there is now a margin inside the edges of the card in the
					Card Design Panel.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>The other two checkboxes only affect the card when printed:</para>
			<itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
				<listitem>
					<para>"Print Inside Card Margins" checkbox determines whether you
					can place cards up to the edges of your cardstock. When this
					checkbox is checked, the cards are placed to ensure that their
					edges are inside the printer's page margins; when not checked,
					cards may be placed at the edges of the cardstock.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>"Fill Last Page With Blank Cards" checkbox determines if the
					last sheet of cardstock will be filled with cards with no QSO information
					printed in the QSOs Box. In many cases, the number of cards
					being printed is not evenly divisible by the number of cards
					that are printed on each page. This wastes cardstock. In
					order to maximize the use of the cardstock, you can print
					blank cards on the last page in order to fill the cardstock.
					You may use these cards at a later time to write QSO information
					on them rather than print new cards.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Printing Cards</title>
			<para>Select the Print Cards... menu item from the Cards
			dropdown menu. This opens the Print dialog shown below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="printdialog">
				<title>Print Dialog</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/printdialog.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>As you can see, the printer properties and print properties are
			displayed again. The settings in this dialog match the settings for
			the card. This is your last chance to make changes before printing.</para>
			<para>Check the "Print Card Outlines" and "Fill Last Page With Blank Cards"
			checkboxes.</para>
			<para>The third group box on the dialog is the cards layout group box.
			This box shows various card layouts on the cardstock. The white rectangles
			surrounded by blue lines represent the cards, with the cardstock
			shown in pink. If you change paper size and check or uncheck the 
			"Print Inside Printer Margins" checkbox, the cards layouts will change.
			In some cases these changes are subtle and in other cases the number
			of cards that can be printed per page changes.</para>
			<para>For this tutorial, make sure that the paper size is set to either
			Letter or A4 size. The "Print Card Outlines" and "Fill Last Page With
			Blank Cards" checkboxes should also be checked. Click on the radio button at
			the right of the first row of card layouts. Now click on the Preview
			button at the bottom of the dialog. This will create a print preview
			of the cards as shown in the image below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="printpreview">
				<title>Print Preview Dialog</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/printpreview.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>There is a toolbar at the top of the dialog shown in the image below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="printpreviewtoolbar">
				<title>Print Preview Toolbar</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/printpreviewtoolbar.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The buttons
			on this toolbar from left to right are as follows:</para>
			<itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
				<listitem>
					<para>Print the pages.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set zoom factor.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Display one page.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Display two pages.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Display three pages.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Display four pages.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Display six pages.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Close the dialog.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>There is a spin box at the top right of the dialog that allows
			you to scroll through the various pages.</para>
			<para>Press the Display two pages button so that the dialog looks
			like the image above.</para>
			<para>On the first page, the first card contains the two QSOs
			with VA3JNO, with VA3HJ as the manager. The second card contains
			a single QSO with VA3JNO, and the third card contains a single
			QSO with 5C5CW. If the maximum number of QSOs on a card
			had been set to 1, only a single QSO would have been printed
			on each card.</para>
			<para>Note that on the cards with one QSO, the confirming
			text in the QSOs Box is "Confirming 2-Way QSO with ...", and
			the salutation text is "Thanks for the QSO. 73,". On the
			card with two QSOs the texts are "Confirming 2-Way QSOs
			with..." and "Thanks for the QSOs. 73,". The inclusion and
			exclusion of the "s" on "QSO" is controlled by a Count Macro. See the
			<link linkend="macros"><emphasis role='underline'>Macros</emphasis></link>
			chapter for more information.
			</para>
			<para>Now view the second page of cards. The first card is 
			for the QSO with CG3JNO, and the last two cards contain a
			QSOs Box with two empty lines. These cards are printed because
			you checked the "Fill Last Page With Blank Cards" checkbox.</para>
			<para>Every card is surrounded by a black line on all sides
			because you checked the "Print Card Outlines" checkbox.</para>
			<para>You will probably notice that the cards are not centered
			on the cardstock even though we selected the card layout that
			should have centered the cards. In fact, the cards are shifted left
			and up by the size of the left and top margins for your printer.
			Don't worry about this. If you were to click the print button, the
			cards would be printed in the middle of the cardstock; the offset
			in Print Preview is caused by the print processing in .Net.
			More information about printing is included in the 
			<link linkend="outputtingcards"><emphasis role='underline'>Outputting
			Cards</emphasis></link> chapter.</para>
			<para>Close the print preview dialog. Go back and try the
			various print options settings combinations to see the effect
			that each setting has.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Concluding the Tutorial</title>
			<para>You have now concluded this tutorial, but you have
			only scratched the surface of the capabilities of<literal>HamQSLer</literal>.
			Be sure to read the remaining chapters in this user
			manual as they contain more information on every aspect of
			the program and also contain many helpful hints and suggestions
			to get the most out of <literal>HamQSLer</literal>.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
