<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<section>
		<title>HamQSLer</title>
	<para>HamQSLer is a program for 
	designing and printing amateur
	radio QSL cards. HamQSLer is the most 
	feature rich QSL design
	and print program available today. Its capabilities include:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
		<listitem>
			<para>One-sided landscape card;</para>
		</listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>Resizable and movable background image, or no background 
    image;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>Add resizable and movable secondary images;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>Resizable, movable, and editable text fields, including callsign, 
			name and QTH, and a salutation by default;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>User settable default text for the following fields so that 
    you do not have to enter for each card you design:</para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact" mark="opencircle">
        <listitem>
			<para>callsign;</para>
		</listitem>
        <listitem>
			<para>name and QTH; and,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
			<para>salutation</para>
		</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>Add resizable, movable, and editable text fields;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>Macros that can be inserted into text fields;</para>
	</listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>Variable number of QSOs in the QSOs box;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>Choice of date formats in the QSOs box;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>Choice of printing bands or frequencies in the QSOs box;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>Choice of including or not including a QSL column in the QSOs box;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
		<para>User settable defaults for the QSOs box:</para>
		<itemizedlist spacing="compact" mark="opencircle">
			<listitem>
				<para>confirmation text;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>column headers;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>frequencies to be displayed when none provided in 
				QSO;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>text placed in QSL column; and,</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>font used to print the QSOs box text.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>Supports import of ADIF 2.0 files, including support up to
		version 2.2.7;</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>QSOs to be printed may be selected by:</para>
		<itemizedlist spacing="compact" mark="opencircle">
			<listitem>
				<para>band,</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>mode;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>date and time;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>QSL sent and received value;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>individual selection; or,</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>any combination of the above.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>QSOs to be printed may be sorted by date and time, callsign
		 or by QSL bureau;</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>Save cards to be printed as JPEG images for sending 
		or taking to a photo store for printing on 4 by 6 inch or 10 by 15 
		cm photo paper;</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>Print multiple cards per page;</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>Support for commonly available perforated cardstock;</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>Print "blank QSO" cards so that pages are not wasted; 
		and,</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>Automatic checking for program updates.</para>
	</listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   </section>
   <section>
	   <title>Why Another QSL Design And Print Program</title>
   <para>There are a large number of computer programs available for 
   printing QSL cards. A cross-section of these include:</para>
   <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
	   <listitem>
		   <para>QSO logging programs that print cards, or labels for 
		   affixing to preprinted cards;</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Programs that print labels for affixing to preprinted 
			cards;</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Programs that print a single QSO on each card; and,</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Logging programs that provide DDE capability for 
			import into Microsoft Word or similar programs for printing 
			cards.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    <para>They are all limited in one way or another and therefore have 
    never satisfied my requirements. Specifically, they either provide 
    limited or no design capability, or only print one QSO per card. 
    They also tend to waste cardstock because they stop printing when 
    the card for the last QSO is printed on the page. I wanted more!</para>
	<para>Have I succeeded? Well, many of my goals have been satisfied. 
	Each future release of this software will provide greater capabilities 
	and let me at least come closer to my desired goal of providing the 
	best QSL design and print program that money can't buy.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Tips and Cautions</title>
		<para>There are a number of tips and cautions in the various 
		pages of this user manual.</para>

		<tip>
			<para>This is an example of a tip. Tips provide information 
			on simplifying your use of QslDesignAndPrint, or provide 
			information on how to get the most out of the program.</para>
		</tip>
		<caution>
			<para>This is an example of a caution. Cautions provide 
			information about traps and pitfalls in the use of HamQSLer.
			</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
</chapter>
