<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="macros">
	<title>Macros</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction to Macros</title>
		<para>Macros add a powerful feature to <literal>HamQSLer</literal> by providing
		<emphasis>active</emphasis> text. For every macro there is text
		that is displayed on the card in design view, and text that is
		inserted when the cards are printed. These macros may be used
		in any text item and also in the confirming text user preference.
		If you followed the <link linkend='gettingstarted'><emphasis role='underline'>Getting
		Started</emphasis></link> tutorial, you got your first glimpse of Count Macro.</para>
		<para>This discussion will focus on macros used in text items;
		using macros in the confirming text user preference are similar
		to macros within the Text and Macros dialog which you
		will see shortly.</para>
		<para>The image below shows the text area in a text item properties
		panel. If there are no macros used in the text item, then this
		is what you will see: a text box for editing the static text,
		and a button labeled "Macros". If there are macros
		being used in the text item, then only the button is visible.</para>
		<figure xml:id="statictextonly">
			<title>Static Text Only in Text Item Properties</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/statictextonly.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Clicking the button opens the Text and Macros dialog, shown
		with static text only, in the image below.</para>
		<figure xml:id="textonlymacrosdialog">
			<title>Static Text Only in the Text and Macros Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/textonlymacrosdialog.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>To add a macro, place the mouse cursor over the colored
		rectangle that contains the "Static Text" and click the right 
		mouse button to bring up the macros
		context menu, shown below.</para>
		<figure xml:id="macroscontextmenu">
			<title>Macros Context Menu</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/macroscontextmenu.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The context menu permits you to add a macro either before
		or after the static text or macro colored rectangle you opened the
		context menu over. There are a few things to notice:</para>
		<simplelist>
			<member>The Delete menu item cannot be selected when only
			one static text or macro exists.</member>
			<member>Static text items cannot be inserted next to another
			static text item, only next to macros.</member>
		</simplelist>
		<para>The image below shows the dialog after a Manager Macro has
		been inserted after the static text item.</para>
		<figure xml:id="managermacroafter">
			<title>Static Text and Manager Macro in Text and Macros Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/managermacroafter.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Every macro has a section called "Design Text". This is
		the text that is displayed on the card in design mode. In the
		<link linkend='gettingstarted'><emphasis role='underline'>Getting Started</emphasis></link>
		tutorial, this is the "$" in both the confirming
		text in the Qsos Box and in the salutation text item. Other sections
		are specific to the macros. At print time, the Manager Macro
		will place the contents of the Manager field for the QSO on the
		card, or the No Manager Text if the Manager field is empty.
		Any of these fields may be blank.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>See 
			<link linkend='nonkeyboardchars'><emphasis role='underline'>Appendix C</emphasis></link>
			if you want to enter characters that are not available
			on your keyboard.</para>
		</tip>
		<para>Macros may be inserted inside macros anywhere that a static
		text field is allowed. For example, you could add a macro inside
		the Design Text or No Manager Text fields of the Manager Macro,
		but you could not add another macro at the same level as the
		Design Text or No Manager Text sections. While macros may theoretically
		be added to any depth, you should take great care with this facility
		as keeping track of the macro level becomes increasingly difficult
		as macros are added to greater depths.</para>
		<para>The remaining sections in this chapter describe each macro.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>ADIF Macro</title>
		<para>An ADIF Macro prints the contents of an ADIF field on a
		card if the field exists and is not an empty string; otherwise,
		it prints user specified text. The image below shows a view of 
		the ADIF Macro as it would first appear after adding in the
		Text and Macros dialog.</para>
		<figure xml:id="adifmacro">
			<title>ADIF Macro</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/adifmacro.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The contents of an ADIF field may change from one QSO to
		the next. Because of this, you will normally want to print a
		different card every time the contents of the ADIF field changes.
		Checking the "Separate Cards By This ADIF Field" checkbox will
		do this; if you do not check this checkbox, then the contents
		of the ADIF field from the first QSO that is printed on the card
		will be added to the card.</para>
		<para>Add the name of the ADIF field for this macro to the ADIF
		Field text box. Standard ADIF fields are defined in the ADIF
		standard, available at 
		<emphasis role='underline'><link xlink:href="http://www.adif.org">
		http://www.adif.org</link></emphasis>. Be sure to select the
		version of the standard that corresponds to the version specified by
		your logging application. In addition to the fields defined in the
		standard, your logger may also export application specific fields.
		See the documentation for your logger for these fields.</para>
		<para>The field name is not case sensitive; for example, "CALL",
		"call", and "CalL" are all valid.</para>
		<para>The No Field Text section contains the text that would
		be printed if either the ADIF field does not exist for the QSOs,
		or the value of the field is an empty string.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>Do you operate using a number of different callsigns?
			If you do and your exported ADIF file contains the 
			STATION_CALLSIGN field, then you could replace the static
			callsign text item with an ADIF Macro for the STATION_CALLSIGN.
			Be sure to check the "Separate Cards By This ADIF Field"
			checkbox. Then a single card can be used for every one of
			your callsigns.</para>
		</tip>
		<tip>
			<para>QSL bureaus prefer that the callsign of the station
			that is to receive a QSL card be written in the upper right
			or left corner of the back or front of the card. You could
			do this by adding a new text item, positioning it appropriately,
			and including text such as "To: " as well as an ADIF macro
			for the CALL field.</para>
			<para><literal>HamQSLer</literal> does not easily support printing
			this on the opposite side of the card from other text and
			the Qsos Box, but if you properly design your card, it can
			be placed on the same side as these items and still be very
			visible to the sorters at the QSL bureaus.</para>
		</tip>
		<tip>
			<para>You could customize the confirming text in the QSOs
			Box or the salutation text item to contain mode information.
			For example, your salutation could be "Thanks for the CW
			QSOs. 73, " for CW QSOs and so forth.</para>
		</tip>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>ADIF Exists Macro</title>
		<para>The ADIF Exists Macro prints user specified text if the
		ADIF field exists for a QSO and its contents are not an empty 
		string, and
		prints a different user specified text if the field either does
		not exist or the field contents are empty. The image below shows 
		a view of the ADIF Exists Macro.</para>
		<para>This image shows the various sections
		as they would be immediately after the macro has been added to
		the Text and Macros dialog.</para>
		<figure xml:id="adifexistsmacro">
			<title>ADIF Exists Macro</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/adifexistsmacro.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Checking the "Separate Cards By This ADIF Field Exists"
		checkbox will cause a new QSL card to be printed every time 
		that consecutive QSOs have and have not included this ADIF field,
		or the field contents are not empty.</para>
		<para>Add the name of the ADIF field for this macro to the ADIF
		Field text box. Standard ADIF fields are defined in the ADIF
		standard, available at <link
		 xlink:href="http://www.adif.org">
		<emphasis role='underline'>http://www.adif.org</emphasis></link>. Be sure to select the
		version of the standard that corresponds to the version specified by
		your logging application. In addition to the fields defined in the
		standard, your logger may also export application specific fields.
		See the documentation for your logger for these fields.</para>
		<para>The field name is not case sensitive; for example, "CALL",
		"call", and "CalL" are all valid.</para>
		<para>Enter the text that you want to appear on the card in design
		view in the Design Text edit box.</para>
		<para>Enter the text that you want displayed if the ADIF field
		exists in the Field Exists Text section.</para>
		<para>Enter the text that you want displayed if the ADIF field
		doesn't exist in the Field Doesn't Exist Text section.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>If you are a contester, you could use this macro to
			modify the salutation to say "Thanks for the contest QSOs.
			73, " for cards for your contest QSOs and not include the
			"contest" word for non-contest QSOs.</para>
		</tip>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Count Macro</title>
		<para>The Count Macro specifies text that is to be printed when
		the condition is met and text that is printed when the condition
		is not met. When a card with QSOs in the Qsos Box is printed,
		the condition is tested against the number of QSOs being  printed
		in the Qsos Box. If a blank card (i.e. a card without QSOs) is
		printed, the condition is tested against the maximum QSOs count for
		the Qsos Box. This matches the number of blank rows printed on
		the card.</para>
		<para>The image below shows a view of the Count Macro. This image 
		shows the various sections
		as they would be immediately after the macro has been added to
		the Text and Macros dialog.</para>
		<figure xml:id="countmacro">
			<title>Count Macro</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/countmacro.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The Condition radio buttons set the test that is to be
		performed against the Condition Value. The conditions are:</para>
		<simplelist>
			<member>Equals,</member>
			<member>Less than, and</member>
			<member>Greater than.</member>
		</simplelist>
		<para>The Condition Value is the number of QSOs or the max QSOs
		value for the QSOs Box. This value may be set to any value between
		1 and 15, and matches the range of values allowed for maximum QSOs.</para>
		<para>Enter the text you want to be displayed on the card in
		design mode in the Design Text section. This is the "$" text that is
		displayed in the confirming text and the salutation text as set
		in the original user preferences.</para>
		<para>Enter the text that is to be printed when the condition
		is met in the True Text section.</para>
		<para>Enter the text that is to be printed when the condition
		is not met in the False Text section.</para>
		<para>You may reverse conditions by reversing the True Text and
		False Text texts.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>The confirming text in the Qsos Box and the salutation
			text defined in the original user preferences (set when you
			start <literal>HamQSLer</literal> for the first time) each contain a Count Macro.
			As used there, the design text is "$", "s" is printed when
			the number of QSOs (or the max QSOs count for blank cards)
			is greater than 1 and no text is printed when the number of
			QSOs is 1.</para>
			<para>It would appear that the use of this macro is limited
			to cases such as this.</para>
		</tip>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Manager Macro</title>
		<para>The Manager Macro prints the contents of the Manager
		column in the QSOs tab if this field is a valid callsign, and
		prints user defined text if the manager's callsign is not valid.</para>
		<para>The image below shows the various sections
		as they would be immediately after the macro has been added to
		the Text and Macros dialog.</para>
		<figure xml:id="managermacro">
			<title>Manager Macro</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/managermacro.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Enter the text you want displayed on the card in design
		mode into the Design Text section.</para>
		<para>Enter the text you want printed when there is no valid
		manager in the No Manager Text section.</para>
		<para>See the Manager Exists Macro section, below, for one use
		of this macro.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Manager Exists Macro</title>
		<para>The Manager Exists Macro prints one set of user defined
		text if the manager field exists and its contents are a valid
		callsign, and another set of user defined text if the field is
		empty or does not contain a valid callsign.</para>
		<para>The image below shows the various sections
		as they would be immediately after the macro has been added to
		the Text and Macros dialog.</para>
		<figure xml:id="managerexistsmacro">
			<title>Manager Exists Macro</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/managerexistsmacro.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Enter the text that you want to be displayed in card design
		mode in the Design Text section.</para>
		<para>Enter the text that you want printed when the manager
		field exists and is a valid callsign in the Exists Text section.</para>
		<para>Enter the text that you want printed on the card when the
		manager field does not exist, or its contents is not a valid
		callsign.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>QSL bureaus prefer that the callsign of the station
			that is to receive a QSL card be written in the upper right
			or left corner of the back or front of the card. You could
			do this by adding a new text item, positioning it appropriately,
			and including text such as "To: " or "Via: " as well as a
			Manager Exists Macro for the manager field. In the Exists
			Text section, add a Manager Macro so that the callsign of
			the manager is printed after the "To: " or "Via: " text.</para>
			<para><literal>HamQSLer</literal> does not easily support printing
			this on the opposite side of the card from other text and
			the Qsos Box, but if you properly design your card, it can
			be placed on the same side as these items and still be very
			visible to the sorters at the QSL bureaus.</para>
		</tip>
		</section>
</chapter>
