<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="outputtingcards">
	<title>Outputting Cards</title>
	<para>Cards can be output in a number of different ways, including printing on a
	printer, and saving images of the cards as JPEG files. Each of these methods
	is described in the sections below, but first, how do you determine the number
	of cards that will be printed?</para>
	<section>
		<title>Determining the Number of Cards That Will Be Printed</title>
		<para>The number of cards that will be printed is determined by the
		total number of QSOs selected, and the maximum number of QSOs that can
		printed on a card. Other factors are the order that the QSOs are sorted,
		and any macros containing ADIF fields that are used on the card.</para>
		<para>To determine the number of cards that will be printed, select the
		Cards -> Calculate Number of Cards to be Printed... menu item. This opens
		the dialog shown in the image below. The number of cards shown in the
		dialog corresponds to the QSOs that were loaded, selected and sorted in
		the <link linkend="gettingstarted">Get Started tutorial</link>, and the
		card that was designed in that tutorial.</para>
		<para>To determine the number of sheets of cardstock that are needed, divide
		the number of cards by the number of cards that will be printed per page,
		and round up.</para>
		<figure xml:id="numberofcards">
			<title>Number of Cards to be Printed Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/numberofcards.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Printing Cards</title>
		<section>
			<title>Defining Custom Paper Sizes</title>
			<para>There are 118 standard paper sizes defined in the Windows operating system. These
			sizes are defined for paper and envelopes. Some paper sizes cannot be supported on some
			printer models because these paper sizes are larger than the largest paper size that the
			printer can handle. For example, A3 paper is 297 by 420 mm (approximately 11.7 by
			16.5 inches). This paper cannot be inserted into a printer whose width is limited to
			US letter (8 1/2 inches or 216 mm wide) or A4 (210 mm or 8.3 inches wide) paper. In
			some other cases, the printer manufacturer may decide not to support a printer size
			because it is a size that is rarely used.</para>
			<para>Most printers support defining custom paper sizes, either on a system wide
			basis, or for a single print job. In the former case, the paper size is defined once
			for the printer and it becomes available to all programs that allow the user to
			select the paper size. In the latter case, the custom paper size is available only
			for one print job; if the paper size is needed again, it must be defined in the next
			print job.</para>
			<para>The following two subsections show how to define a system wide custom paper size for
			printers that support it, and a tool for defining a custom paper size in HamQSLer that
			is saved so that it may be reused in future card print jobs. In both subsections, a
			custom paper size for bureau cards will be created.</para>
			<section>
				<title>Defining a System Wide Custom Paper Size</title>
				<para>As mentioned above, this method only works if your printer supports it.</para>
				<para>Open the Devices and Printers dialog, available from the Start menu and from
				the Control Panel. The dialog is called Printers and Faxes in Windows XP. This dialog
				looks similar to the image below.</para>
				<figure xml:id="devicesandprinters">
					<title>Devices and Printers Dialog</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/devicesandprinters.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>This image shows the Devices and Printers dialog on my computer which runs
				Windows 7. The printers and faxes are listed in the second section of the dialog.
				To define a custom paper size, move the mouse cursor over the printer you want to
				define the paper size for, and click the right mouse button to bring up the context
				menu. Select the Printing preferences menu item. This will display the printing
				preferences dialog, which probably contains a number of tabs with labels such as
				Printing Shortcuts, Features, and Advanced. Select the Features tab. You should then see
				a panel similar to the image below, which is what is displayed on Windows 7 for HP
				printers.</para>
				<figure xml:id="featurestab">
					<title>Features Panel on Printing Preferences Dialog</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/featurestab.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>The size dropdown box, highlighted above, shows the default paper size for the
				printer. Click on the dropdown box to open it. The contents will look similar to the
				image below.</para>
				<figure xml:id="papersizesdropdown">
					<title>Features Panel on Printing Preferences Dialog</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/papersizesdropdown.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>The dropdown contains one or more standard paper sizes, and may contain custom
				paper sizes that you defined in the past. If you select the More... item, a dialog
				is opened that allows you to change the default paper size for your printer. Any custom
				paper sizes that you define are probably listed at the bottom. Since we are not
				interested in changing the default paper size, you can ignore this menu item.</para>
				<para>The last menu item is Custom... If this item is present, you can define
				custom paper sizes; if it is not present,
				then you must set your custom paper sizes using the method
				in the section below. Click on the Custom... item to open the custom paper size
				dialog, shown in the following image. If your printer is not manufactured by HP, or you
				are not running Windows 7, then
				the dialog will not look exactly like this.</para>
				<figure xml:id="hpcustompapersizedialog">
					<title>Custom Paper Size Dialog</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/hpcustompapersizedialog.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>To define a custom paper size for bureau cards, enter a Width of 3.5 inches or
				88.9 mm, and enter a Length of 5.5 inches or 139.7 mm. Change the name to
				<emphasis>Bureau Card</emphasis> or whatever else you want to call your card. When
				you change the paper size name, the Save button becomes active. Click this button
				to save the new custom paper size, then click the OK button to close the dialog. Your new
				custom paper size will be available from the standard print dialog that is displayed
				when you print from most programs. This paper size will also be available from the
				print dialog in HamQSLer. Printing cards in HamQSLer is discussed below.</para>
				<tip>
					<para>Always set the width in the custom paper size dialog to the smaller dimension
					of your custom paper size, and the length to the larger dimension. HamQSLer assumes
					that the paper sizes are set for Portrait mode.</para>
				</tip>
				<caution>
					<para>Your printer may limit the number of custom paper sizes that you
					can define. If you need to define additional paper sizes for use
					with HamQSLer, use the method described in the following section.</para>
				</caution>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Defining a Custom Paper Size for HamQSLer Only</title>
				<para>If your printer does not support setting system wide custom paper sizes, you
				may use the method described here to create a custom size that can be used only
				within HamQSLer.</para>
				<para>To define a custom paper size, select the Tools -> Define Custom
				Paper Sizes menu item. This opens the custom paper sizes dialog shown in
				the image below.</para>
				<figure xml:id="custompapersizes">
					<title>Custom Paper Size Dialog</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/custompapersizes.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>The Name dropdown box contains the names of all custom paper sizes
				you have already defined in HamQSLer and the word
				<emphasis>Custom</emphasis>. To make changes to any of the paper sizes
				you have defined, select that paper size name. Otherwise, select
				<emphasis>Custom</emphasis>. Note that <emphasis>Custom</emphasis>
				is the default value when you open this dialog.</para>
				<para>The text box below the dropdown contains the name of the custom
				paper size you are working with. When you select a paper size from the
				dropdown, the text in this text box is automatically set to the name
				you selected.</para>
				<para>To define a new bureau card paper size, select
				<emphasis>Custom</emphasis>. The paper size that is displayed is the
				default paper size on the default printer on your
				computer system. Enter a width of
				3.5 inches or 88.9 mm and a height of 5.5 inches or 139.7 mm. Change
				the name from <emphasis>Custom</emphasis> to <emphasis>Bureau
				Card</emphasis> or similar. When you change the name from 
				<emphasis>Custom</emphasis> to
				another value, the Save button is enabled. Click this button to save the
				new paper size, then click the Close button to close the dialog.</para>
				<para>This new paper size will be displayed at the end of the
				paper sizes in the paper size dropdown
				in the print dialog for HamQSLer.</para>
				<tip>
					<para>Always enter the smaller paper dimension in the width field
					and the larger dimension in the height field. HamQSLer assumes the
					paper sizes are defined in Portrait mode.</para>
				</tip>
				<caution>
					<para>Only use this method to define custom paper sizes if you cannot
					define a system wide custom paper size for your printer. Defining
					a custom paper size using the instructions in this section means
					that the paper size is available in HamQSLer only.</para>
				</caution>
				<caution>
					<para>The custom paper sizes created using this method are stored
					in the user preferences file. If you delete, move, or lose this file,
					the custom paper sizes are lost along with all other user preferences
					settings. You will then have to redefine your custom paper sizes.</para>
				</caution>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Print Modes and Printer Margins</title>
			<para>Most printers support two modes of printing: borderless and bordered printing.
			Borderless printing is normally used for printing photographs. The printer increases
			the image size by a few percent to ensure that the image is larger than the paper
			size so that the image being printed completely covers the paper. A small portion
			of the edges of the image are outside the boundaries of the paper. This is
			usually not noticed when you print a photograph, but will be noticeable if
			you print multiple QSL cards in borderless mode, especially if you select a
			cards layout on the page where the one or more cards is positioned at the edges
			of the page. Here is an example of four bureau sized cards printed along
			the top edge of a sheet of letter sized paper in borderless mode.</para>
			<figure xml:id="borderlessprint">
				<title>Borderless Print</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/borderlessprint.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Compare the left sides of the cards on the left with the left sides
			of the cards on the right. Notice that the left edge of the cards
			on the left have been clipped. Similarly, the right side of the cards on the
			right have been clipped. Now compare the top edge of the cards at the top with
			the cards on the row below. Again, the top of the cards at the top have been
			clipped. You should only select a borderless paper size if you are centering
			the cards on the page, or are printing on a paper size that is the same size
			as the cards being printed.</para>
			<para>Now, let's look at bordered printing. In this mode, every printer has
			a minimum margin along each edge of the paper. These minimum margins vary from
			printer model to printer model and may not be the same size on each side.
			For example, the HP Officejet 6500 printer has margins of 0.125 inch (3.175 mm)
			on every side; the HP Photosmart 7960 series printers have minimum margins of
			0.125, 0.07, 0.135, and 0.583 inch or 3.175, 1.778, 3.429, and 14.817 mm.
			How do you determine the minimum margins for you printers? HamQSLer
			includes a tool for that. See <link linkend="minimummargins">
			Determining Printer Minimum Margins</link> below.</para>
			<para>Obviously mimimum margins would lead to a problem if you attempted to 
			print cards	using a cards layout that positioned the cards on one or more edges 
			of the page. The edges of the cards that are positioned at the edges of the page
			are clipped, producing a white margin on those edges. Provided the minimum margins are less than
			0.25 inch or 6.35 mm, HamQSLer has a setting that allows you to clip the printing
			around the edges of each card to match the largest minimum margin for the
			printer. See <link linkend="printerprops">Printer Properties and
			Print Properties</link>, below for more information.</para>
		</section>
		<section xml:id="minimummargins">
			<title>Determining Printer Minimum Margins</title>
			<para>As discussed above, printer minimum margins determine where on a page you
			can actually print. HamQSLer provides a tool to enumerate these margins. To open
			the tool, select the Tools -> Show Printer Margins.</para>
			<para>The printer minimum margins dialog opens. The printer dropdown box
			lists all of the printers installed on the user's computer, with the default
			printer selected, and the margins listed below the dropdown. The image below
			shows the result on my computer.</para>
			<figure xml:id="margins6500">
				<title>Printer Minimum Margins Dialog</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/margins6500.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The margins are displayed in a dark green color, and as you can see,
			all margins are the same size.</para>
			<figure xml:id="margins7960">
				<title>Printer Minimum Margins Dialog - Uneven Margins</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/margins7960.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para> The image above shows the printer minimum
			margins with the HP Photosmart 7960 series printer selected. The margins are
			all different sizes, and the bottom margin is greater than 0.25 inch or 6.35 mm.
			The value for this margin is displayed in red, and a warning message is shown
			below the margins. The meaning of the message is discussed in the next section.
			</para>
			<para>The minimum printer margins are a physical property of each printer,
			are set by the printer manufacturer, and are not user changeable.</para>
		</section>
		<section xml:id="printerprops">
			<title>Printer Properties and Print Properties</title>
			<para>Printer settings and print settings may be set in three locations:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>The settings in user preferences are program default settings.
					These settings are transferred to the card file when a new card is
					created.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Each card has a set of card specific default settings. The card
					specific default printer and print settings should be set to values
					that the user would normally use when printing that card.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Finally, when the user selects the Print Cards... menu item,
					the card specific print and printer settings are copied to the
					print dialog, where the user can modify them for that specific
					print job.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>The image below shows the printer properties and print properties
			in the card properties panel. The same properties are displayed in the
			user preferences dialog; these properties are also displayed in the
			print dialog when printing cards.</para>
			<figure xml:id="printerproperties">
				<title>Printer and Print Options Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/printerprops.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<section>
				<title>Printer Properties</title>
				<para>The printer dropdown box contains a list of all of the printers
				that are installed on the computer. The paper size dropdown box lists all
				of the paper sizes for the selected printer, and the quality dropdown box lists
				all of the print resolution values for the selected printer. Finally, the paper
				source dropdown lists all of the papersources or trays for the selected
				printer. If there is only one paper source, this dropdown box is disabled.
				</para>
				<para>When the user selects a different printer, the paper size, quality,
				and paper source dropdowns are reloaded with the lists that are valid
				for the newly selected printer. An attempt is then made to set the
				selected values to the previously selected values. For example, if the
				paper size for the first printer was selected to be A4, then when a new
				printer is selected, an attempt is make to select A4 as the paper size.
				Similarly, an attempt is made to select the previous quality and paper
				source values. If these values cannot be found in the list, then the
				default paper size, quality, and paper source values for the newly selected
				printer are selected.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>Even though the same paper sizes may exist on multiple printers,
					the name given to these paper sizes may be different. As a result,
					the printer's default paper size would be selected. For example,
					the name for the A4 paper size on the HP OfficeJet 6500 is
					<emphasis>A4 210x297mm</emphasis> and the name on the HP Photosmart
					7960 series of printers is <emphasis>A4</emphasis>. So, even though
					the paper size is A4 in both cases, the names are different, and
					when the user switches between these printers, the default paper
					size would be selected in the paper size dropdown box.</para>
					<para>Similarly, the quality and paper source selected values
					may be set to the newly selected printer's default values.</para>
				</caution>
				<tip>
					<para>The default printer and its default properties may be set in the
					Devices and Printers section of the Control Panel.</para>
				</tip>
				<para>The default printer, paper size, quality, and paper source in the
				user preferences are set to the default computer values when the user
				preference file is created. Any changes made by the user in the user
				preferences dialog are saved to the user preferences file.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>If the printer that is set in user preferences is uninstalled,
					the printer and printer properties will be reset to those for the
					new default printer on the computer.</para>
				</caution>
				<para>When a card is created, the printer and printer properties that
				are stored in user preferences are used to initialize the same values
				for the card.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>If the printer that is set for the card is uninstalled,
					then the printer and printer properties for the card will be reset 
					to those for the new default printer on the computer.</para>
				</caution>
				<para>Finally, when the print dialog is opened during printing, 
				the printer and printer properties in the
				print dialog are set to the values set for the card.</para>
				<para>Set the user preferences printer properties to the values that
				you would normally use for printing QSL cards. There may be instances
				where, for a specific QSL card, you would want to normally print them
				on a different printer or with different printer properties. For example,
				you may have a number of bureau sized QSL cards designed that you would
				print on one printer using either letter or A4 sized cardstock, but also 
				have a 4 inch by 6 inch card that you
				would want to print on a photo printer using 4 inch by 6 inch photo paper
				instead. For this, you would set
				the user preferences to the printer and properties that you will be using
				for most cards, and set the card specific printer and properties of the
				larger card to those for your photo printer.</para>
				<para>Finally, when you print the cards, you can change the printer
				and printer settings again for that specific printer job. One place
				you may want to do this is if you are not at your normal workplace or
				home and want to print some cards using someone else's printer.</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Print Properties</title>
				<para>There are four print properties, two of which are related to
				printer margins, and two which are not. We will first look at the two
				that are not affected by print margins.</para>
				<para>The Print Card Outlines checkbox determines whether a black line
				is printed around the edge of the cards. This outline is useful for
				cutting the cards from the cardstock after printing. If the checkbox
				is checked, the outline is printed; if the checkbox is not checked,
				the outline is not printed.</para>
				<para>If this checkbox is checked in the card properties panel, the
				outline is also displayed on the card in design mode.</para>
				<para>When printing a number of cards on cardstock, the total number
				of cards being printed may not be evenly divisible by the number of
				cards per page. If they are not, then the last page being printed would
				contain less than a full page of cards. This is wasteful of cardstock.
				The user may print additional cards with no QSOs printed in the
				QSOs Box on the last page and fill in the QSO data by hand at a later
				time. Filling the last page is accomplished using the Fill Last Page
				With Blank Cards checkbox. With the checkbox checked, the blank cards
				will be printed; with the checkbox unchecked, no blank cards are printed.
				</para>
				<para>Printer margins were discussed in the Print Modes and Printer
				Margins section, above. As mentioned, the printer margins determine how
				close to the edge of a page the printer will print. The first print
				property that is affected by the printer margins is the Set Card
				Margins to Printer Margins checkbox. Checking this checkbox leaves
				a margin around the inside of each card equal to the size of the widest
				margin for the selected printer. With the checkbox unchecked, the contents
				of the card are printed to all edges of the card. This checkbox also
				has an effect in card design mode; if the checkbox is checked, the margin
				is displayed on the card. The image below shows the card created in
				the Getting Started chapter with the Set Card Margins to Printer
				Margins checkbox checked. The Print Card Outlines checkbox was also
				checked to better show the card edges. As you can see, there is a
				clean margin around the inside edges of the card. This margin allows
				the user to print cards out to the edges of the cardstock without
				only one or two edges having margins and without uneven margins.</para>
				<figure xml:id="cardmargins1">
					<title>Card With Printer Margins</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/cardmargins1.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>If you want to print cards without a margin, you cannot print to
				the edges of the page. The Print Inside Printer Margins checkbox determines
				whether the cards can be printed to the edges of the cardstock or must
				be printed inside the printer margins. Checking the checkbox forces the
				cards to be printed inside the printer margins; unchecking the checkbox
				allows cards to be printed up to the edges of the cardstock. As you will
				learn in the Print Cards section which follows, unchecking this checkbox
				does not force cards to be printed on the edges of the cardstock. There
				are a number of ways to layout the cards on the cardstock; this setting
				simply allows the user to select a cards layout that prints cards out
				to the edges of the cardstock.</para>
				<para>What happens if the maximum printer margin is large. Have a look at
				the following image.</para>
				<figure xml:id="cardmargins2">
					<title>Card With Large Printer Margins</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/cardmargins2.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>In this image, the margins are 14.8 mm or 0.58 inch. As you can see,
				this does not look good at all and there is little space for actual card
				content. For this reason, if the largest printer margin is greater than
				0.25 inch or 6.35 mm, the Print Inside Printer Margins checkbox is checked,
				the Set Card Margins to Printer Margins checkbox is unchecked, and both
				checkboxes are disabled so that the user cannot change their settings.
				This forces cards to be printed with no margins and inside the printer
				margins for the cardstock.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Printing Cards</title>
			<para>HamQSLer prints cards with QSO information in the QSOs Box on each card.
			If no QSOs are loaded or selected for printing, then a single page of cards
			with no QSO information in the QSOs Box is printed.</para>
			<caution>
				<para>The cards are printed with QSOs in the order that they are sorted
				in the QSOs tab. Be sure to sort the cards in the order you want them
				printed.</para>
			</caution>
			<para>To print cards, the card must be loaded into the program, and the card's
			tab must be selected. That is, the card must be displayed in the program's
			main window.</para>
			<para>Select the Cards -> Print Cards... menu item. This will open the
			print cards dialog which is shown in the image below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="printdialog2">
				<title>Print Cards Dialog</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/printdialog.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The printer properties and print properties group boxes are the same
			as in the user preferences dialog and the card properties panel. The values
			in the controls in these group boxes are loaded with same values as the controls
			in the card properties panel. This is the user's last chance to make
			changes to these properties before the cards are printed. Any changes made
			only affect this print job; the card properties are not modified by changes
			made in the print cards dialog.</para>
			<para>There is one additional group box in the dialog: the cards layout
			group box. The radio buttons displayed in this box show how the cards will
			be laid out on the cardstock when they are printed. For each layout, the
			cards are displayed in white with a blue line around them. The area in
			light pink shows the cardstock on which the cards will be printed. In each
			row of layouts, the cards are laid out as follows: top left card is positioned
			at the top left corner of the cardstock, top left card is centered left to
			right and positioned at the top of the cardstock, and finally, the cards are
			printed to be centered on the cardstock. In the image above, the first row
			shows the layouts for cards printed on cardstock in portrait orientation, and
			the second row shows the layouts in landscape orientation.</para>
			<para>If cards cannot be printed on the cardstock in one of the orientations,
			then that row of layouts is not displayed in the dialog. For example, the
			image below shows the cards layout group box for bureau sized cards on
			4 by 6 inch paper. Because the card width is greater than the 4 inches,
			cards cannot be printed on the paper in portrait orientation, so the
			portrait layouts are not shown.</para>
			<figure xml:id="cardslayoutlandscapeonly">
				<title>Cards Layout Landscape Only</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/cardslayoutlandscapeonly.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>If the paper size selected is smaller than the size of the cards
			to be printed, then only a warning message is shown. See the image below for
			an example.</para>
			<figure xml:id="nocardlayouts">
				<title>Print Cards Dialog With Paper Size Too Small</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/nocardlayouts.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The message "The selected paper size is smaller than the card size. No cards
			can be printed." is displayed in red in the cards layout group box and the Print
			and Preview buttons are disabled.</para>
			<para>As mentioned previously, checking the Print Inside printer Margins checkbox
			affects the layout of cards on the cardstock. The cards are printed so that
			the edges of the cards are at or inside the printer margins. The image below
			shows the layouts for bureau sized cards on letter sized cardstock. It is
			not easy to see, but in portrait mode, the cards in the first two layouts have
			been moved to the left and down.</para>
			<para>There is a much greater effect on the layouts
			in landscape mode. Bureau cards are 5.5 inches wide and letter sized paper is
			11 inches wide in landscape mode. So, two cards can just be printed across
			the paper in landscape mode. However, if the cards are to be printed inside the
			printer margins, then only one card wide can be printed. Compare this image
			to the image in Figure 9.7. The only difference in settings is that the
			Print Inside Printer Margins is checked for Figure 9.10.</para>
			<figure xml:id="cardsinsidemargins">
				<title>Cards Layouts Inside Margins</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/cardsinsidemargins.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<tip>
				<para>There are three manufacturers of cardstock that is micro-perforated
				for printing of bureau sized cards. In all cases, the cardstock is letter
				sized (8 1/2 by 11 inches). The QSLKit provides cardstock for printing four
				cards per page using the top left or top center landscape layout.
				QslPaper.com provides cardstock for printing four cards per
				page using the center landscape layout. Yourofficestop.com provides
				3UPPCSTOCK cardstock for printing 3 cards per page using the center
				portrait layout.</para>
				<para>Avery provides a number of letter sized, micro-perforated 
				cardstocks for printing four 4.25 by 5.5 inch cards per page.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>The print cards dialog contains three buttons: Print, Preview, and Cancel.
			These buttons perform the expected functions.</para>
			<para>Selecting the Print button prints the cards. A message box, like the one
			in the image below is displayed and updated for each page of cards as
			they are printed. When the last past page is printed, the message
			box disappears.</para>
			<figure xml:id="printing">
				<title>Printing Message Box</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/printing.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Printing is an asynchronous operation. As a print job is performed, the
			output is queued to the printer queue, and control returns to the program.
			Only then will the printer start printing the cards. This has a number of
			advantages:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>The program does not have to wait for the printer to finish
					printing before it regains control.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Print jobs may be queued to the printer so that the user
					does not have to wait for a print job from another program to
					finish before he can print cards.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Print jobs may be queued to printers that are offline
					(disconnected, powered down, etc.) and the print jobs will remain
					in the queue until the printer is brought online.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>Selecting the Preview button displays the print preview dialog and
			the message box shown in the image above is displayed until the last page
			of cards is processed. The first page of cards is displayed in the print
			preview dialog. For example, the image below shows the print preview dialog
			as displayed if you followed the <link linkend="gettingstarted">Getting 
			Started tutorial</link>.</para>
			<figure xml:id="printpreview1">
				<title>Print Preview Dialog</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/printpreview1.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The first thing to notice is that the cards as displayed on the
			page in the dialog are shifted up and to the left by an amount equal to the
			minimum left and top printer margins. This is an artefact of the print
			preview processing. If these cards are printed, they will be positioned
			properly on the cardstock and not as shown in the print preview.</para>
			<para>There are a number of buttons and other controls on the toolbar at the
			top of the dialog. The following table describes what each button and control
			does.</para>
			<table frame='all'>
				<title>Print Preview Toolbar Controls and What They Do</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname="Control" colwidth='70pt'/>
					<colspec colname="Description"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry namest='Control'>Control</entry>
							<entry namest='Description'>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/previewprint.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Print the cards. This is equivalent to clicking the
								Print button in the print dialog.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/previewzoom.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Adjust magnification of the preview</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/preview1.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Display one page</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/preview2.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Display two pages</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/preview3.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Display three pages</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/preview4.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Display four pages</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/preview6.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Display six pages</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/previewclose.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Close preview dialog</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<inlinemediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/previewpage.png"/>
									</imageobject>
								</inlinemediaobject>
							</entry>
							<entry>Show this page number</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Saving Card as a JPEG</title>
		<para>A card, with or without QSO data, may be saved as a JPEG file for display
		on a website or for sending over the Internet. To do this, select the Cards ->
		Save Card as Jpeg... menu item. This opens the JPEG Image Properties dialog
		which is shown below.</para>
		<figure xml:id="saveasjpeg">
			<title>JPEG Images Properties Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/saveasjpeg.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The various controls in this dialog set properties of the
		image. If you want to include QSO data in the image, then check the Show QSOs
		checkbox. The card in the image will contain the QSOs that would appear on the 
		first card if you were printing cards.</para>
		<para>The resolution dropdown box contains three commonly used values; 96 DPI
		is the value to use for displaying cards on a computer, such as from a website.
		This corresponds approximately to the typical resolution of a computer monitor,
		so the cards will appear about lifesize on the monitor.
		300 and 600 DPI are good values for printing or for sending to a QSL card printer.
		The dropdown box value is also editable so you can enter any value you want.</para>
		<para>JPEG files use a lossy compression when they are saved, so when a file is
		saved, its quality will decrease somewhat. The quality dropdown box contains a number
		of values that control the amount of compression that is applied when the card
		is saved. Quality values vary between 0 and 100, with 100 being the best
		quality. Even at 100, there is some compression applied.</para>
		<para>There is a link between quality and the size of the image file; the
		higher the quality setting, the larger the file size. For example, take the sample
		card that was created in the <link linkend="gettingstarted">Getting
		Started tutorial</link>. The table below shows the size of the file that
		is created at each of four quality values, with the resolution set to 300 DPI.</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>JPEG Quality Versus File Size</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
				<colspec colname="Quality" colwidth='75pt'/>
				<colspec colname="FileSize" colwidth='75pt'/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='Quality'>Quality</entry>
						<entry namest='FileSize'>File Size</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>75</entry>
						<entry>193 kB</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>85</entry>
						<entry>245 kB</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>95</entry>
						<entry>357 kB</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>100</entry>
						<entry>804 kB</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>When the user clicks the OK button, a Save As dialog opens so that
		a file name for the image file may be entered, and a directory may be selected
		to save the file in.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>There is no discernable difference in quality of the image between 95 and
			100, yet the file size for an image saved at 100 is more than twice the size
			of the same image saved at 95. The best compromise between image quality and
			file size is 85. The card images that are displayed on the website are saved
			at 85. Some images have been saved two or three times at this quality setting.
			</para>
		</tip>
		<caution>
			<para>If an image is saved as a JPEG, and then loaded into an image editing
			program and resaved multiple times, the quality of the image will gradually
			decrease. However, even with a quality of 85, an image may be resaved a
			few times before there is any discernable loss of quality when the image
			is displayed.</para>
		</caution>
		<tip>
			<para>If you want to have your QSL card added to the sample cards on the website,
			please use the following settings: Show QSOs checked, resolution of 96 DPI,
			quality of 85.  Because of the use of macros in the card, QSOs should be
			printed on the card. You can use the QSOs that are included in the sample.adi 
			file
			in the Samples directory. I promise not to claim credit for any QSOs that are
			included on the card.</para>
		</tip>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Saving 4-Up Bureau Cards For Printing</title>
		<para>HamQSLer allows the user to save a set of four blank bureau-sized cards
		as a JPEG file for sending to a print shop or a QSL card printer for
		printing large quantities of the the cards. To save the blank cards, select
		the Cards -> Save 4-Up Cards For Printing... menu item. This action opens the
		dialog shown in the image below.</para>
		<figure xml:id="fourupcards">
			<title>JPEG Image Properties for 4 Up Blank Bureau Cards Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/4upcards.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>There are only two options available: the Include Card Outlines checkbox
		controls whether a black line is included around the outside of the card or not,
		and the resolution dropdown box controls the resolution that the image is saved at.
		There are only two values provided in this dropdown box: 300 DPI and 600 DPI. These
		are standard values that are used when printing. The dropdown box is also editable,
		so you can enter any value that you wish.</para>
		<para>When the OK button is clicked a Save As dialog box opens to allow the user
		to enter a name for the file, and to select a directory to save the file in. When
		the image has been saved, the message "Card image has been saved to 
		<emphasis>(filename)</emphasis> is displayed in the status bar of the main
		window.</para>
		<para>The cards are saved in a two by two array. The image is 7 by 11 inches in
		size, so the image may be printed lifesize on either letter or A4 sized cardstock.
		</para>
		<caution>
			<para>Only bureau sized cards may be saved as a set of 4-up cards.</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Saving Cards For Printing</title>
		<para>Instead of printing cards with QSO data on them, the cards may be saved in
		a set of JPEG files for sending or taking to a photo print shop. To create these
		image files, the user must select the Cards -> Save Cards For Printing... menu
		item. When this is done, the browse for folder dialog box, shown below, is
		displayed.</para>
		<figure xml:id="cardsforprinting">
			<title>Browse For Folder Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/cardsforprinting.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The user must select a directory to save the image files in. Once
		the directory has been selected and the OK button is clicked, the card images
		are generated and saved in the selected directory. The files are saved with
		filenames <emphasis>qslXXX.jpg</emphasis>, where XXX is a number that is
		incremented for each card.</para>
		<para>Filenames start at qsl1.jpg. If the selected directory already contains
		files named qslXXX.jpg, then the number in the filename of the first file saved
		is set to one more than the highest value of XXX. That is, if there is a file 
		called qsl25.jpg in the directory,
		the first file saved will be qsl26.jpg.</para>
		<para>As the files are being created, the text "Creating card X of Y cards" where
		X is the number of the card being created and Y is the total number of cards
		being created is displayed in the status bar of the main window. When all of the
		files have been created, the text "Y of Y cards created in directory:
		<emphasis>(directory)</emphasis>" is displayed in the status bar.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>Create a subdirectory in the hamqsler directory to contain the card
			images. Name the file <emphasis>Printing</emphasis> or something similar so
			that you know what the directory contains.</para>
		</tip>
		<caution>
			<para>The card images are placed in an image that is 4 by 6 inches (10 by
			15 cm) in size. Because of this, only bureau cards and 4 by 6 inch cards may be
			saved for printing.</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
</chapter>
