<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="programinit">
	<title>Program Initialization and the Splash Screen</title>
	<section>
		<title>Program Initialization</title>
		<para>When <literal>HamQSLer</literal> starts, it performs a number of intialization 
		steps. These steps are:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Displays the splash screen.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Checks if the <filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename> directory 
				and its subdirectories
				exist and create them if they do not. Copies any initial files to the directories.
				These files include <filename>sample.jpg</filename> and 
				<filename>sample.adi</filename> that are needed in the
				<link linkend="gettingstarted"><emphasis role='underline'>Getting
				Started</emphasis></link> chapter.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Checks if the <filename class='directory'>HamQSLer</filename> directory
				exists in the <filename class='directory'>AppDataFolder</filename>. The
				<filename class='directory'>AppDataFolder</filename> is the directory
				<filename class='directory'>C:\User\</filename><emphasis>username</emphasis><filename class='directory'>\AppData\Roaming</filename>
				on Windows 7 systems. It may be located in a different location
				on computers running other versions of Windows. If the directory does
				not exist, it is created.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The existence of the file <filename>AdifEnumerations.xml</filename>
				in the <filename class='directory'>AppData</filename> is checked. If the
				file does not exist, it is copied from the within the program
				to the <filename class='directory'>AppData</filename> directory.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Creates a new log file.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Writes runtime information to the log file. This information includes the version
				numbers of the program and data files, the version number of the .Net runtime,
				and other information that may be useful to the developers should the program
				abort for some reason.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Loads user preferences from the user preferences file, or creates the file
				if it is not found.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Retrieves program and data file version information from the website, and
				informs the user if new versions are available. Downloads the
				<filename>AdifEnumerations.xml</filename> file from the website
				if a new version of the file is available.</para>
				<tip>
					<para>A setting is provided in user preferences to turn on or turn off checking for
					new program and data file versions. See the 
					<link linkend="settinguserprefs"><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User
					Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter for more information.</para>
				</tip>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If there is initialization status to convey to the user, shows the Continue and/or
				Terminate button on the splash screen. If there is not initialization information
				that the user needs to know about, opens the main window and closes the splash screen.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Splash Screen</title>
		<para>Information about
		what initialization is being performed, and any conditions that the user must
		be informed of are displayed on the splash screen. For example, the splash screen shown
		below is what the user would probably see the first time he starts 
		<literal>HamQSLer</literal>. There are
		messages informing the user that the <filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename>
		directories were created and files copied
		to them, and the User Preferences file was created because it could not be found.</para>
		<figure xml:id="firstsplashscreen2">
			<title>Splash Screen First Time HamQSLer Started</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/firstsplashscreen.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>A list of all of the messages that may be displayed in the splash screen are included
		below. Some messages simply inform the user that certain initialization tasks are being performed;
		these messages disappear when the tasks are completed. For example, there is a message stating
		that the program is checking for new program and data file versions. If new versions of files
		are found, messages about the new files are displayed.</para>
		<para>Once initialization has completed, if there is no information to be presented to the user,
		then the <literal>HamQSLer</literal> main window opens and the splash screen closes. 
		If there are messages for
		the user, then the splash screen is displayed, along with one or two buttons: Continue and
		Terminate. The user must select one of these buttons before the program can continue. Obviously,
		if the user clicks the Terminate button, then the program will terminate. This action would be
		useful if there is a new version of the program available for the user to download and install.
		If the user clicks the Continue button, the main program window opens and the splash screen
		closes.</para>
		<variablelist>
			<title>Splash Screen Messages and Their Meanings</title>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Created hamqsler directories in and/or copied Samples 
								files to your 'Documents' directory.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The <filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename> directory, one or 
					more of its default 
					subdirectories, or the sample files were not found. The directories have been
					created and/or the sample files have been copied.</para>
					<para>The <filename class='directory'>HamQSLer</filename> directory in
					<filename class='directory'>AppData</filename>, or the
					<filename>AdifEnumerations.xml</filename> file has been created or copied.</para>
					<para>This message is most likely
					to appear the first time that you start <literal>HamQSLer</literal>. 
					If it appears later than
					the first execution of the program, then one or more of the files or directories
					was deleted prior to starting <literal>HamQSLer</literal>.</para>
					<para>The list of directories created and files copied is placed in the log file.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Problem creating hamqsler directories or copying 
							files to your 'Documents' directory</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>An error occurred while attempting to create the 
					<filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename> directory, 
					one of its subdirectories,
					or while attempting to copy the sample files. A MessageBox has
					already been displayed to show the cause of the error.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>You do not have the required permission to access log file.
					You may continue to use HamQSLer but no logging will be done.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The local security settings on this computer do not let you create
					the log file. You must discuss this problem with the person who set up your
					computer. For more information, see 
					<link xlink:href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/33tceax8(v=vs.100).aspx">
					<emphasis role='underline'>Code Access Security Basics</emphasis></link>.</para>
					<para>As stated in the message, you may continue to use <literal>HamQSLer</literal>
					but no logging
					will be done. Realistically, if you receive this message, you will probably
					encounter many other problems with <literal>HamQSLer</literal>. 
					The only solution is to fix the
					security settings problems; that topic is beyond the scope of 
					<literal>HamQSLer</literal> and this document.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>You cannot access the log file. You may continue to use HamQSLer
				but no logging will be done.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Access permissions for the log file prevent you from creating a
					new log file. There could be several reasons for this, but the most
					likely cause is that the log file or the 
					<filename class='directory'>Logs</filename>
					directory have been set to be read-only.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Error occurred while attempting to access user
					  preferences file. Preferences have been created.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The user preferences file (<filename>.hamqsler</filename>) could not
					be accessed for some reason. A MessageBox has already been displayed giving
					the reason for the error. As stated, a new user preferences file and object
					have been created and initialized. If this is not the first time that you
					have run <literal>HamQSLer</literal>, then any user preference settings you 
					changed in the past have been lost.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>User preferences file did not exist. It has been created.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>A new user preferences file has been created. If this is not the
					first time that you have started <literal>HamQSLer</literal>, \
					then any setting changes you made in the past have been lost.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Error occurred attempting to retrieve update information. See
							 Log file for details of error.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The program versions file could not be retrieve from the website.
					There are many possible causes for this. A MessageBox has already been displayed
					giving more information about the actual cause of the error.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>New stable version of HamQSLer is available.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>A new stable (release) version of <literal>HamQSLer</literal>
					 is available. Go to the website to download it.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>New development version of HamQSLer is available.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>A new development version of <literal>HamQSLer</literal> is available. 
					Go to the website to download it.</para>
					<tip>
						<para>A setting is provided in user preferences to turn on or turn off checking for
						new development versions of the program. See the 
						<link linkend="settinguserprefs"><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User 
						Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter for more information.</para>
					</tip>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Checking for program update and data file revisions.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>As stated, <literal>HamQSLer</literal> is checking for updates to the 
					program and
					associated data files. This message is displayed only while the checking is
					being performed, and will disappear as soon as the checking is completed,
					regardless of whether the versions file could be retrieved from the website
					or not. Other messages will be displayed if there were any errors with
					the versions file, or if new versions are available.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Error occurred loading AdifEnumerations file. Will load default file.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>An error occurred while attempting to load the
					<filename>AdifEnumerations.xml</filename> from
					<filename class='directory'>AppData</filename>. There are many reasons
					for this. See the log file for information on the error.</para>
					<para>The original <filename>AdifEnumerations.xml</filename>
					file that was included with this version of <literal>HamQSLer</literal>
					will be loaded.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>New AdifEnumerations file downloaded.</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>A new version of the
					<filename>AdifEnumerations.xml</filename> has been downloaded
					from the website. The version number of the file is printed
					to the log file.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
</chapter>
