<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="settinguserprefs">
	<title>Setting User Preferences</title>
	<para>User preferences control a number of aspects of program execution and contain many text
	and QSOs Box related properties. Depending on some of the user preferences settings,
	HamQSLer may save additional information in the user preferences file. For example, if the setting
	for restoring ADIF files is set, then the paths to all ADIF files that were loaded would be saved
	with the user preferences so that HamQSLer could load these files when the program starts.</para>
	<para>User preferences are written to a text file called <emphasis>.hamqsler</emphasis> and
	stored in the <emphasis>hamqsler</emphasis> directory. This file is loaded during program
	initialization. See the <link linkend="programinit">Program Initialization and the Splash
	Screen</link> chapter for more information.</para>
	<para>Users edit user preferences settings by using the User Preferences dialog. This dialog
	is displayed by selecting the Edit->User Preferences menu item on the main window. When first
	opened, the dialog looks like the image below.</para>
	<figure xml:id="userprefsdialog2">
		<title>User Preferences Dialog When First Opened</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/userprefsdialog.png" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para>User preferences are arranged in a set of topics. For example, Program contains settings
	that affect how HamQSLer executes, and TextItems contains settings related to text items. The
	default font face for text items and the default callsign, name and QTH, and salutation that
	are placed on a card when it is first created are examples of texit item settings.</para>
	<para>The box on the left of the dialog contains the set of topics in expander controls. To open
	an expander, either click on the arrowhead to the left of the topic, or double-click on the topic
	name. The image below shows the topics with all expanders opened.</para>
	<figure xml:id="userprefstopics">
		<title>User Preferences Topics</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/userprefstopics.png" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para>Clicking on any of the subtopics displays a panel of controls on the right side of the
	dialog. These controls may be set by the user to changed the corresponding user preference.</para>
	<para>Each of the topics and settings is discussed in the sections that follow.</para>
	<section>
		<title>Program Settings</title>
		<para>Program settings affect the execution of HamQSLer during program initialization.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Program Version Check</title>
			<para>The image below shows the user preferences dialog with the Program
			Version Check subtopic selected. There are only two settings, one for
			checking for new versions of the program and data files, and one for
			also checking for new development releases.</para>
			<figure xml:id="programversioncheck">
				<title>Program Version Check Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/programversioncheck.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The Check for Program and Data File Updates checkbox controls whether HamQSLer
			checks for new program and data file versions during initialization. With the
			checkbox checked, the program checks for new versions, and with the checkbox
			unchecked, the program does not check for new versions. The
			default value (the value set when the user preferences file is first created)
			is to check for new versions.</para>
			<para>The Stable and Development Program Releases checkbox determines whether
			HamQSLer should check only for data file updates and stable program
			updates, or if it should also check for development updates. if this checkbox
			is checked, then HamQSLer checks for both stable and development new
			releases during program initialization. If unchecked, HamQSLer checks only 
			for new stable releases. The default value is to not check for development
			versions.</para>
			<para>Development
			versions of HamQSLer are provided to allow users access to new features as they
			are developed rather than waiting for a stable release. You can think of
			development releases as beta releases of the program.</para>
			<para>This checkbox can only be checked or unchecked if the Check for Program
			and Data File Updates checkbox is checked.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>Development releases give users access to new features as they
				are being developed rather than waiting for the final release.</para>
			</tip>
			<caution>
				<para>Development releases have not necessarily been tested as
				thoroughly as stable releases, so more bugs may be encountered in
				a development release that its subsequent stable release. Of course,
				if no one uses the development release, then the bugs won't be found
				until the stable release.</para>
			</caution>
		</section>
			<section>
				<title>HTTP Proxy Settings</title>
				<para>The image below shows the user preferences dialog with the HTTP Proxy
				Settings subtopic selected. These controls configure HamQSLer to use an
				HTTP proxy. Most users do not need to modify the default settings.</para>
				<figure xml:id="httpproxysettings">
					<title>Proxy Settings Preferences</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/httpproxysettings.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>The proxy server control is used to specify the name or IP address
				of the HTTP proxy server. The default value is no server.</para>
				<para>The proxy server port is the port number for the HTTP proxy server.
				The default value is 80, which is the standard port number for HTTP servers.
				Other typical port numbers are 8000, 8080, and 8888.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>Change these settings only if HamQSLer cannot retrieve the versions
					file during program initialization. Internet service providers typically
					do not require you to configure proxy servers on their networks, so
					proxy server settings are only required if your network has one installed.
					This is not something that is typically done on a home network.</para>
					<para>Even if a proxy server is installed on your network, it would
					normally be configured in Control Panel->Internet Options, so there
					would be no need to configure the server here.</para>
				</caution>
			</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Files and Folders</title>
		<para>These user preferences subtopics contain preferences related to ADIF,
		card, and images files and folders.</para>
		<section>
			<title>ADIF Files and Folder</title>
			<para>This subtopic contains preferences specifying whether HamQSLer should
			reload ADIF files when the program starts, and the directory that the
			file open dialog should open in when handling Import QSOs... and Add QSOs...
			menu items processing. The image below shows the user preferences dialog
			with the ADIF Files and Folder subtopic selected.</para>
			<figure xml:id="adiffilesandfolder">
				<title>ADIF Files and Folder Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/adiffilesandfolder.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The Reload ADIF Files on Startup checkbox setting determines whether ADIF
			files are reloaded or not when HamQSLer starts up. With the checkbox checked,
			the files are loaded; with the checkbox unchecked, the files are not
			loaded.</para>
			<para>The files that are reloaded are determined by the user's use of four
			menu items from the QSOs dropdown menu:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting the Clear QSOs menu item also clears the 
					ADIF files reload list.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting the Import QSOs... menu item clears the
					ADIF files reload list, and then adds the the newly selected
					ADIF file to the list.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting the Add QSOs... menu item adds the newly selected
					ADIF file to the list.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting the Export QSOs... menu item clears the
					ADIF files list and then add the file to which the QSOs were exported
					to the list.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>The ADIF files list is stored in the user preferences file but there
			is no way for the user to see the list except by opening the user
			preferences file in a text editor.</para>
			<caution>
				<para>If the user opens the user preferences file in a text editor, he
				must be certain not to make any changes to the file; in other words,
				if a change is made accidentally, the user must not save the file.
				Editing the user preferences file could result in HamQSLer aborting
				or otherwise malfunctioning.</para>
			</caution>
			<para>The Default ADIF Files Folder is the directory that HamQSLer opens
			in a File Open dialog when the user selects either the Import QSOs... or
			Add QSOs... menu item. The user should set this value to the directory in which
			he stores ADIF files.</para>
			<para>To change the folder, click on the button labeled "..." that is
			located to the right of the folder name. This opens a Folder Browser
			dialog from which the user may select a new directory.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
