<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="settinguserprefs">
	<title>Setting User Preferences</title>
	<para>User preferences control a number of aspects of program execution and contain many text
	and QSOs Box related properties. Depending on some of the user preferences settings,
	HamQSLer may save additional information in the user preferences file. For example, if the setting
	for restoring ADIF files is set, then the paths to all ADIF files that were loaded would be saved
	with the user preferences so that HamQSLer could load these files when the program starts.</para>
	<para>User preferences are written to a text file called <emphasis>.hamqsler</emphasis> and
	stored in the <emphasis>hamqsler</emphasis> directory. This file is loaded during program
	initialization. See the <link linkend="programinit">Program Initialization and the Splash
	Screen</link> chapter for more information.</para>
	<para>Users edit user preferences settings by using the User Preferences dialog. This dialog
	is displayed by selecting the Edit->User Preferences menu item on the main window. When first
	opened, the dialog looks like the image below.</para>
	<figure xml:id="userprefsdialog2">
		<title>User Preferences Dialog When First Opened</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/userprefsdialog.png" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para>User preferences are arranged in a set of topics. For example, Program contains settings
	that affect how HamQSLer executes, and TextItems contains settings related to text items. The
	default font face for text items and the default callsign, name and QTH, and salutation that
	are placed on a card when it is first created are examples of texit item settings.</para>
	<para>The box on the left of the dialog contains the set of topics in expander controls. To open
	an expander, either click on the arrowhead to the left of the topic, or double-click on the topic
	name. The image below shows the topics with all expanders opened.</para>
	<figure xml:id="userprefstopics">
		<title>User Preferences Topics</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/userprefstopics.png" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para>Clicking on any of the subtopics displays a panel of controls on the right side of the
	dialog. These controls may be set by the user to changed the corresponding user preference.</para>
	<para>Each of the topics and settings is discussed in the sections that follow.</para>
	<section>
		<title>Program Settings</title>
		<para>Program settings affect the execution of HamQSLer during program initialization.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Program Version Check</title>
			<para>The image below shows the user preferences dialog with the Program
			Version Check subtopic selected. There are only two settings, one for
			checking for new versions of the program and data files, and one for
			also checking for new development releases.</para>
			<figure xml:id="programversioncheck">
				<title>Program Version Check Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/programversioncheck.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The Check for Program and Data File Updates checkbox controls whether HamQSLer
			checks for new program and data file versions during initialization. With the
			checkbox checked, the program checks for new versions, and with the checkbox
			unchecked, the program does not check for new versions. The
			default value (the value set when the user preferences file is first created)
			is to check for new versions.</para>
			<para>The Stable and Development Program Releases checkbox determines whether
			HamQSLer should check only for data file updates and stable program
			updates, or if it should also check for development updates. if this checkbox
			is checked, then HamQSLer checks for both stable and development new
			releases during program initialization. If unchecked, HamQSLer checks only 
			for new stable releases. The default value is to not check for development
			versions.</para>
			<para>Development
			versions of HamQSLer are provided to allow users access to new features as they
			are developed rather than waiting for a stable release. You can think of
			development releases as beta releases of the program.</para>
			<para>This checkbox can only be checked or unchecked if the Check for Program
			and Data File Updates checkbox is checked.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>Development releases give users access to new features as they
				are being developed rather than waiting for the final release.</para>
			</tip>
			<caution>
				<para>Development releases have not necessarily been tested as
				thoroughly as stable releases, so more bugs may be encountered in
				a development release that its subsequent stable release. Of course,
				if no one uses the development release, then the bugs won't be found
				until the stable release.</para>
			</caution>
		</section>
			<section>
				<title>HTTP Proxy Settings</title>
				<para>The image below shows the user preferences dialog with the HTTP Proxy
				Settings subtopic selected. These controls configure HamQSLer to use an
				HTTP proxy. Most users do not need to modify the default settings.</para>
				<figure xml:id="httpproxysettings">
					<title>Proxy Settings Preferences</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/httpproxysettings.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>The proxy server control is used to specify the name or IP address
				of the HTTP proxy server. The default value is no server.</para>
				<para>The proxy server port is the port number for the HTTP proxy server.
				The default value is 80, which is the standard port number for HTTP servers.
				Other typical port numbers are 8000, 8080, and 8888.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>Change these settings only if HamQSLer cannot retrieve the versions
					file during program initialization. Internet service providers typically
					do not require you to configure proxy servers on their networks, so
					proxy server settings are only required if your network has one installed.
					This is not something that is typically done on a home network.</para>
					<para>Even if a proxy server is installed on your network, it would
					normally be configured in Control Panel->Internet Options, so there
					would be no need to configure the server here.</para>
				</caution>
			</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Files and Folders</title>
		<para>These user preferences subtopics contain preferences related to ADIF,
		card, and images files and folders.</para>
		<section>
			<title>ADIF Files and Folder</title>
			<para>This subtopic contains preferences specifying whether HamQSLer should
			reload ADIF files when the program starts, and the directory that the
			file open dialog should open in when handling Import QSOs... and Add QSOs...
			menu items processing. The image below shows the user preferences dialog
			with the ADIF Files and Folder subtopic selected.</para>
			<figure xml:id="adiffilesandfolder">
				<title>ADIF Files and Folder Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/adiffilesandfolder.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The Reload ADIF Files on Startup checkbox setting determines whether ADIF
			files are reloaded or not when HamQSLer starts up. With the checkbox checked,
			the files are loaded; with the checkbox unchecked, the files are not
			loaded.</para>
			<para>The files that are reloaded are determined by the user's use of four
			menu items from the QSOs dropdown menu:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting the Clear QSOs menu item also clears the 
					ADIF files reload list.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting the Import QSOs... menu item clears the
					ADIF files reload list, and then adds the the newly selected
					ADIF file to the list.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting the Add QSOs... menu item adds the newly selected
					ADIF file to the list.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting the Export QSOs... menu item clears the
					ADIF files list and then add the file to which the QSOs were exported
					to the list.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>The ADIF files list is stored in the user preferences file but there
			is no way for the user to see the list except by opening the user
			preferences file in a text editor.</para>
			<caution>
				<para>If the user opens the user preferences file in a text editor, he
				must be certain not to make any changes to the file; in other words,
				if a change is made accidentally, the user must not save the file.
				Editing the user preferences file could result in HamQSLer aborting
				or otherwise malfunctioning.</para>
			</caution>
			<para>The Default ADIF Files Folder is the directory that HamQSLer opens
			in a File Open dialog when the user selects either the Import QSOs... or
			Add QSOs... menu item. The user should set this value to the directory in which
			he stores ADIF files.</para>
			<para>To change the folder, click on the button labeled "..." that is
			located to the right of the folder name. This opens a Folder Browser
			dialog from which the user may select a new directory.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Cards Files and Folder Preferences</title>
			<para>This subtopic contains preferences specifying whether HamQSLer should
			reload card files when the program starts, and the directory that the
			file open dialog should open in when handling the Open Card... 
			menu item processing. The image below shows the user preferences dialog
			with the Card Files and Folder subtopic selected.</para>
			<figure xml:id="cardfilesandfolder">
				<title>Cards Files and Folder Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/cardfilesandfolder.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The Reload Card Files on Startup checkbox setting determines whether card
			files are reloaded or not when HamQSLer starts up. With the checkbox checked,
			the files are loaded; with the checkbox unchecked, the files are not
			loaded.</para>
			<para>The files that are reloaded are determined by the card files that are
			open when HamQSLer is terminated. New cards that have not been saved are
			not reloaded.</para>
			<para>The card files list is stored in the user preferences file but there
			is no way for the user to see the list except by opening the user
			preferences file in a text editor.</para>
			<caution>
				<para>If you open the user preferences file in a text editor, 
				be certain not to make any changes to the file; in other words,
				if a change is made accidentally, do not save the file.
				Editing the user preferences file could result in HamQSLer aborting
				or otherwise malfunctioning.</para>
			</caution>
			<para>The Default Card Files Folder is the directory that HamQSLer opens
			in a File Open dialog when the user selects the OpenCard
			menu item. The user should set this value to the directory in which
			he stores ADIF files.</para>
			<para>To change the folder, click on the button labeled "..." that is
			located to the right of the folder name. This opens a Folder Browser
			dialog from which the user may select a new directory.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Images Folder Preferences</title>
			<para>This subtopic contains a single preference, the default images folder.
			This specifies the directory that the file open dialog is opened in when the
			user adds a background or secondary image to the card in design mode.</para>
			<figure xml:id="imagesfolder">
				<title>Images Folder Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/imagefilesfolder.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The image above shows the user preferences dialog with the Images
			Folder subtopic selected. To change the directory, click on the button
			labeled ... to the right of the folder name. This opens the Folder
			Browser dialog from which the user may select a new directory.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Text Items Preferences</title>
		<para>The text items topic contains user preferences that are related to
		text items in general and the default callsign, name and QTH, and salutation
		texts that are added to a new card when it is created.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Default Text Font Preference</title>
			<para>The default text font is the font that text items are displayed in
			when a new card is created. All text items are displayed in this font on
			the new card. However, the user may later select a different font for each
			text item on the card. See the <link linkend="carddesign">Working With
			Cards</link> chapter for more information.</para>
			<para>The user preferences dialog with the default font face subtopic
			selected is shown in the image below. The only preference available
			in this panel is the Default Text FontFace. A list of all fonts
			registered on the computer is provided in a dropdown box. When HamQSLer
			is executed for the first time, the default text font face is set to
			Arial.</para>
			<figure xml:id="defaulttextfont2">
				<title>Default Text Font Preference</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaulttextfont.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Select the font you want as the default from the dropdown box. A
			sample of text in that font is displayed in the box below the
			dropdown box.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Default Callsign Text Preference</title>
			<para>The default callsign text is the callsign that is placed on a new card
			when it is first created. The image below shows the user preferences dialog with
			the Callsign Text subtopic selected. In this image, there is a text box with the
			text "MyCall" in it, and a Macros button below it. When the user preferences file is
			created, either the first time that HamQSLer is started, or if HamQSLer cannot locate
			the user preferences files and creates a new one, the default callsign is set to "MyCall".
			</para>
			<figure xml:id="callsigntext2">
				<title>Default Callsign Text Preference</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultcallsign2.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>You may either edit the callsign text, or click on the Macros button to set the
			default callsign to a set of macros. See the <link linkend="macros">Macros</link>
			chapter for more information.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>If you always use the same callsign, change "MyCall" to that callsign. If you
				followed the <link linkend="gettingstarted">Getting Started</link> tutorial,
				then you have already performed this step.</para>
			</tip>
			<tip>
				<para>If you use a number of different callsigns and the callsign that is used for each
				QSO is stored in your QSO database and exported to an ADIF file, then you should
				follow one of more of the tips in the AdifMacro and AdifExistsMacro sections of the
				<link linkend="macros">Macros</link> chapter. See the documentation for your
				logging program to determine the ADIF fields that the logging program uses.</para>
			</tip>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Default Name and QTH Text Preference</title>
			<para>The default name and QTH text is placed on a new card when it is first
			created. The image that follows this paragraph shows the user preferences
			dialog with the Name and QTH Text subtopic chosen. In this image, there is a
			text box with the text "MyQth" in it and a Macros button below it. When the user
			preferences file is first created, the default text is set to "MyQth".</para>
			<figure xml:id="nameQth2">
				<title>Default Name and QTH Text Preference</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultnameQth2.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Change "MyQth" to your name and address. Use the Enter key to separate lines
			of text.</para>
			<para>As an alternative, you could create a set of macros by clicking the Macros
			button, although it is unlikely to be very useful. Why would you want QSL cards
			sent to different addresses?</para>
			<tip>
				<para>If you operate from different locations such as at home, at your
				cottage, and as a rover during contests, add a new text item to the card
				and place the operating location in it. See <link linkend="carddesign">Working
				With Cards</link> for information about adding text items to a
				card.</para>
			</tip>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Default Salutation Text Preference</title>
			<para>The default salutation text is placed on a new card when it is first
			created. The first image below shows the user preferences dialog with the
			Salutation Text subtopic selected. Note that there is no text box, just a
			Macros button. This is what you would see the first time that you select this
			subtopic. There is no text box because the default salutation text contains
			macros, and therefore you must open the Static Text and Macros dialog by clicking
			on the Macros button to edit
			the salutation.</para>
			<figure xml:id="salutatoin">
				<title>Default Salutation Text Preference</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultsalutationtext.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The image that follows shows the Static Text and Macros dialog box as
			it would appear if you have not edited the salutation before. Note that there
			is a Static Text group box with a text box containing the text "Thanks for the
			QSO" in it, a Count Macro group box, and finally, another Static Text group
			box with the text ". 73," in it. The count macro is discussed in the
			<link linkend="macros">Macros</link> chapter, so it will not be discussed in
			detail here.</para>
			<para>As currently set up, the salutation text that is displayed on a new
			card in design mode is "Thanks for the QSO$. 73,". When you print cards, if
			you set the maximum number of QSOs that can be printed on a card to 1, or the
			maximum number of QSOs is set to greater than 1, but only one QSO is being
			printed on the card, then the salutation text that is printed is "Thanks for
			the QSO. 73,". If the maximum number of QSOs is set to greater than 1 and no
			QSOs are being printed or there is more than 1 QSO being printed on the card,
			then the salutation text printed on that card would be "Thanks for the QSOs.
			73,".</para>
			<figure xml:id="defaultsalutation2">
				<title>Default Salutation Text Macros</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultsalutation.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<tip>
				<para>If you make changes to the count macro for this salutation,
				you may want to make similar changes to the confirming text preference
				in the QSOs Box Preferences, which is discussed below.</para>
			</tip>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>QSOs Box Preferences</title>
		<para>The QSOs Box preferences topic contains user preferences that are related
		to the display of text items in the QSOs Box, such as the font face that all
		text in the QSOs Box is displayed in, the contents of the headers in each
		column of the box, and the frequency values printed for QSOs whose records contain
		a band field but no frequency field.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Default QSOs Box Font Preference</title>
			<para>The default QSOs Box font is the font that all text in the QSOs Box
			is displayed in when a new card is created. While designing a card, the user 
			may select a different font. See the <link linkend="carddesign">Working With
			Cards</link> chapter for more information.</para>
			<para>The user preferences dialog with the default QSOs Box font face subtopic
			selected is shown in the image below. The only preference available
			in this panel is the Default QSOs Box FontFace. A list of all fonts
			registered on the computer is provided in a dropdown box. When HamQSLer
			is executed for the first time, the default QSOs Box font face is set to
			Arial.</para>
			<figure xml:id="defaultqsosboxfont">
				<title>Default QSOs Box Font Preference</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultqsosboxfont.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>Select the font you want as the default from the dropdown box. A
			sample of text in that font is displayed in the box below the
			dropdown box.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Confirming Text Preference</title>
			<para>The confirming text is placed on the first line of the QSOs box of a
			card. The first image below shows the user preferences dialog with the
			Confirming Text subtopic selected. Note that there is no text box, just a
			Macros button. This is what you would see the first time that you select this
			subtopic. There is no text box because the default confirming text contains
			macros, and therefore you must open the Static Text and Macros dialog by clicking
			on the Macros button to edit
			the text.</para>
			<figure xml:id="confirmingtext">
				<title>Default Confirming Text Preference</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/confirmingtext.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The image that follows shows the Static Text and Macros dialog box as
			it would appear if you have not edited the confirming text before. Note that there
			is a Static Text group box with a text box containing the text "Confirming 2-Way
			QSO" in it, a Count Macro group box, and finally, another Static Text group
			box with the text "with" in it. The count macro is discussed in the
			<link linkend="macros">Macros</link> chapter, so it will not be discussed in
			detail here.</para>
			<para>As currently set up, the confirming text that is displayed on a 
			card in design mode is "Confirming 2-Way QSO$ with". When you print cards, if
			you set the maximum number of QSOs that can be printed on a card to 1, or the
			maximum number of QSOs is set to greater than 1, but only one QSO is being
			printed on the card, then the confiming text that is printed is "Confirming
			2-Way QSO with". If the maximum number of QSOs is set to greater than 1 and no
			QSOs are being printed, or there is more than 1 QSO being printed on the card,
			then the salutation text printed on that card would be "Confirming
			2-Way QSOs with".</para>
			<figure xml:id="defaultconfirmingtext">
				<title>Default Confirming Text Macros</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/defaultconfirmingtext.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<tip>
				<para>If you make changes to the count macro for this confirming text,
				you may want to make similar changes to the salutation text preference
				in the Text Items Preferences, which is discussed above.</para>
			</tip>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Date Formats Preferences</title>
			<para>These preferences refer to the format that dates should be printed
			in, and the header text for the date column in the QSOs Box.</para>
			<figure xml:id="dateheaders">
				<title>Date Formats Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/dateheaders.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The image above shows the user preferences dialog with the Date Formats
			subtopic selected. The dropdown box at the bottom of the panel contains all of
			the formats that the dates may be printed in. Currently the choices are:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>YYYY-MM-DD. This is the date in ISO 8601 format.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>DD-MMM-YY.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>DD-MM-YY.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>Select the date format that you want to be the default date format when
			a new card is created. This may be changed to a different format when designing
			a card.</para>
			<para>The choice of format determines the header text that is displayed in the
			date column in the QSOs Box. Edit the header text for each
			date format using the text boxes above the dropdown box.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>What does 02-04-03 mean? It depends on the country you live in, among
				other things. For the answer to this question and a discussion of 
				meaningful date formats, see
				<link xlink:href="www.w3.org/QA/Tips/iso-date">Use international
				date format</link>.</para>
			</tip>
			<caution>
				<para>As noted in the tip above, 02-04-03 can mean different dates in
				different countries. If you do use DD-MM-YY as the date format on
				your card, do not change the header text to something like "Date" as
				this may bring back the confusion as to what the date actually is.</para>
			</caution>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Header Text Preferences</title>
			<para>This subtopic allows the user to set the header text for
			the Time, Band, Frequency, Mode, and RST columns.</para>
			<para>The image below shows the user preferences dialog with the Header
			Text subtopic selected. There is one text box for each of the five
			headers.</para>
			<para>Modify the header text to the text that you want for each column. The
			text may be a maximum of 6 characters. The header text for the QSOs Box
			on a card is fixed to these values when a card is creating. In other words,
			changing the preferences only affects new cards that the user creates.</para>
			<figure xml:id="headertext">
				<title>Header Text Preferences</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/headertexts.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<caution>
				<para>The values that are printed in the frequency column are in MHz,
				so don't change the header to indicate kHz.</para>
			</caution>
			<caution>
				<para>If you delete all text from one of the text boxes, the default
				text will be used when printing the card. In other words, column headers
				in the QSOs Box are never blank when designing and printing a card.</para>
			</caution>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
