<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="workingwithqsos">
	<title>Working With QSOs</title>
	<para>The majority of HamQSLer users make use of a QSO logging program; logging programs
	vary in functionality from simple, basically equivalent to a computerized paper log, up
	to complex programs that track awards, monitor and control transmitters and receivers, 
	interact with digital modems, and communicate with electronic QSLing services such as 
	Logbook of the World
	and eQSL. The one common component that exists in all modern logging programs is the
	ability to exchange data with other programs using Amateur Data Interchange Format (ADIF).</para>
	<para>The ADIF standard has existed for many years, and has gone through many changes over
	that time. The standard is very flexible in that it specifies the various fields that can
	be contained in a QSO record, but does not mandate that all or even a specific subset of the fields
	is required in every record. The one requirement that ADIF makes for any program that claims
	compatibility with any version of the standard is that it must accept as input ADIF files that were
	generated to any version of the ADIF standard that preceeds the standard that the receiving program
	claims compatibility with.</para>
	<caution>
		<para>HamQSLer attempts to follow the ADIF standard but in a few places does not. In general,
		this does not cause a problem because HamQSLer is only interested in a few of the fields
		that appear in QSO records in an ADIF file. Compatibility with the latest ADIF standard is
		one of the first sets of changes that will be made to HamQSLer once it has been released.</para>
	</caution>
	<caution>
		<para>HamQSLer validates QSO records to ensure that they contain at least a minimum set of
		data: start or end date and time for the QSO, frequency or band used, mode used for the QSO,
		and the callsign of the station contacted. A number of validity checks are performed on the
		data that is input via ADIF. For example, if a frequency is specified, it must be within
		the ADIF specified ham bands, and the callsign must be valid. More information on the checking
		that HamQSLer does to each QSO record being input is provided in the Importing QSOs section,
		below.</para>
	</caution>
	<para>A number of users may still keep paper logs. HamQSLer provides a dialog for manually inputting
	QSOs one at a time. This facility may be used as the only means of inputting QSOs, or may be
	used in addition to loading QSO data from ADIF files.</para>
	<para>This chapter discusses importing QSO data from ADIF files, inputting QSOs using the input
	dialog, sorting the QSOs and selecting QSOs to be printed on QSL cards.</para>
	<section>
		<title>Loading and Saving QSOs</title>
		<para>In order to work with QSOs, including loading and saving them, the QSOs tab in the
		main window of the program must be selected. When the QSOs tab is selected, the QSOs dropdown
		menu becomes active, along with the menu items that are valid at that time. The menu items
		are:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Input QSOs... - this opens an input QSO dialog for entering QSOs manually.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Import QSOs... - this opens an Open File dialog to select an ADIF file to import
				QSOs from. Any QSOs which may have already been loaded into HamQSLer are removed
				before the new QSOs are loaded.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Add QSOs... - this opens an Open File dialog to select an ADIF file to import
				QSOs from. These QSOs are added to any QSOs that may already be loaded into the
				program.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Clear QSOs - this deletes any QSOs that are loaded into the program.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Export QSOs... - this opens a File Save dialog to save the loaded QSOs to an
				ADIF file.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Each of these menu items is discussed below.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Inputting QSOs</title>
			<para>QSOs may be input manually by selecting the Input QSOs... menu item. Selecting
			this menu item opens the Input QSO dialog as shown in the image below.</para>
			<figure xml:id="inputqsosdialog2">
				<title>Input QSO Dialog</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/inputqsosdialog.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The dialog contains a number of text boxes and dropdown boxes that allow the
			user to enter data about a QSO. This dialog allows entry of only those fields that
			are used normally by HamQSLer.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>If additional QSO fields are required, then the user
				should use an appropriate QSO logging program, then export the QSOs to an ADIF file,
				and import that file into HamQSLer.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>As a minimum, the callsign, start date, start time, mode, and band or frequency
			values must be entered in this dialog. Once valid values have been entered in these boxes,
			the Add+ and OK buttons are enabled to allow the QSO to be stored in the QSOs view.</para>
			<para>The Add+ button validates the contents of the QSO fields, then adds the QSO to the 
			list of QSOs in the QSOs view, and deletes the
			contents of all boxes in the dialog to prepare for entry of the next QSO. The OK button
			validates the contents of the QSO fields, then adds the QSO to the list of QSOs in the 
			QSOs view and closes the Input QSO dialog. The
			Cancel button closes the dialog without adding an entered QSO into the QSOs view.</para>
			<section>
				<title>Validating a QSO Input via the Input QSO Dialog</title>
				<para>In the image, several of the text boxes are outlined in red. See
				<link linkend="errorhandlingandlogging">Error Handling and Logging</link> for a discussion
				of input validation and the reason that these text boxes are outlined.</para>
				<para>The value entered into the callsign text box must be a valid callsign. A callsign
				is determined to be valid if it matches one of the following:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>One or two letters followed by one or more numbers followed by
						one or more letters.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>A single number followed by one or two letters followed by one or
						more numbers followed by one or more letters.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>A callsign that do not match the formats listed above. A list of valid
						non-standard callsigns is maintained and read by the program. A non-standard
						callsign must be in the list to be considered valid. Some examples of valid
						non-standard callsigns are BX100, LM9L40Y, and OEH20.</para>
						<para>Any non-standard callsign that is shown in the ARRL DX bulletin,
						issued weekly, is added to the list. HamQSLer users may request that a
						callsign be added to the list by filing an enhancement issue. See the website
						for instructions.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>The callsign may have a leading qualifier followed by "/" or one or more
				trailing qualifiers, with each trailing qualifier preceeded by "/".
				A leading qualifier is
				always a country or territory identifier. The trailing qualifier is typically
				an indicator about the operation, such as /M for mobile, /MM of maritime mobile,
				/AM for aeronautical mobile, /P for portable, /QRP for QRP, and so forth. For
				United States / Canada reciprocal operations, the country/territory identifier
				is appended to the callsign and placed before other trailing qualifiers.
				HamQSLer only checks the callsign for validity, and not
				the leading or trailing qualifiers.</para>
				<para>The manager text box must either be empty, or contain a valid callsign with
				no leading or trailing qualifiers.</para>
				<para>The start date must be exactly 8 digits long, be of the form YYYYMMDD and
				be a date between 19451101 and today.</para>
				<para>The start time must be either 4 digits of the form HHMM, or 6 digits of the
				form HHMMSS. The time must be between 0000 and 2359 or between 000000 and 235959.</para>
				<para>Modes are selected from the mode dropdown box. A mode may be selected by:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Clicking the dropdown box. This opens
						the list of modes; a mode may be selected by clicking on it, or by pressing
						the up and down arrow keys to highlight a mode, and then pressing the
						Enter key. Instead of selecting a mode with the mouse or the up and down
						arrow keys, you may enter the mode using the alphabetic and numeric keys
						on the keyboard. You should continue to enter keys until the desired mode is
						highlighted, then press Enter to select the mode. As an alternative to
						entering the mode by spelling it out, the user may press the first letter
						of the mode multiple times. This will cycle through all modes that begin
						with that letter. </para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Moving focus to the dropdown box by tabbing
						to it, then using the up and down arrow keys on the keyboard to highlight the
						mode, and pressing the Enter key to select it. The dropdown box does not open,
						but the selected mode changes with each press of the up or down arrow keys.
						Instead of moving through the modes using the arrow keys, you may enter
						the mode using the alphabetic and numeric keys on the keyboard. As each key is
						pressed, the mode that most closely matches the entered keys is selected.
						For example, pressing "C" will select the first mode beginning with "C". 
						If you then
						press "L", CLO is selected because it is the first mode that begins with
						"CL". If you press the same letter several times, then the selection will
						cycle through all of the modes that begin with that letter.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>The signal report field accepts any text up to three characters in length. The
				normal values here are RS for analog voice modes, RST for CW and similar modes,
				RSQ for most digital modes, and dB for JT65 and similar modes.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>No validation is performed on the signal report. If you enter text that
					is not representative of "standard" values, the report may not be understood
					by your card's recipient.</para>
				</caution>
				<para>The band and frequency boxes work together, and at least one of these boxes must
				contain a value.</para>
				<para>The band dropdown box contains a list of all ADIF defined amateur
				radio bands. A band may be selected by:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Clicking on the band dropdown box to open it, and then clicking on the
						desired band. Alternatively, once the dropdown box is open, you can press the
						up or down arrow keys
						to highlight a band and then press the Enter key to select it. The third option
						is to enter text to highlight the band. Once the correct band has been highlighted,
						press the Enter key to select it.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Moving focus to the dropdown box by tabbing to it, then using the
						up and down arrow keys to select the desired band. Instead of moving through
						the bands, you may use the keyboard to enter the band. When the first key is
						pressed, the first band in the list that contains that character as the first
						character is selected. As you enter more characters, the first band in the
						list that contains those characters is selected. To cycle through all of the
						bands that start with a character, press that character multiple times. For
						example, the first time you press "1", 160m is selected; the second time you
						press "1", 17m is selected, and so on.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>A frequency may be entered into the frequency text box. The frequency must be
				entered in MHz, and must be within the frequency limits of an ADIF defined band.</para>
				<para>If a band is selected and then a frequency is entered, the frequency is checked
				to ensure that it is within the limits of the selected band. If a frequency is entered first and
				then a band is selected, the band is checked to ensure that the frequency is within that
				band. If the frequency is not within the selected band, then the second value entered
				is shown as being in error.</para>
				<para>The QSL Rcvd, Sent, and Sent Via fields are optional, with values contained in
				dropdown lists. You may select any of the values in the dropdown boxes using the 
				instructions
				provided for selecting a band, above. Because the fields are optional, no validity
				checking is performed on any of the fields.</para>
				<para>The values in the dropdown boxes have the following meanings (defined in
				ADIF).</para>
				<table frame='all' xml:id='QslRcvd'>
				<title>QSL Rcvd Values and Meanings</title>
				<tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='Values' colwidth='60'/>
					<colspec colname='ADIFValues' colwidth='150'/>
					<colspec colname='Meanings' />
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='Values'>Value</entry>
						<entry namest='ADIFValues'>ADIF QSL_RCVD Field Value</entry>
						<entry namest='Meanings'>Meaning</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Yes</entry>
							<entry>Y</entry>
							<entry>An incoming QSL card has been received.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>No</entry>
							<entry>N</entry>
							<entry>An incoming QSL card has not been received.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Requested</entry>
							<entry>R</entry>
							<entry>The logging station (you) has requested a QSL card.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Ignore</entry>
							<entry>I</entry>
							<entry>Ignore this QSO.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Verified</entry>
							<entry>V</entry>
							<entry>DXCC award credit has been granted for this QSO because you
							submitted a card to the ARRL for this QSO and that card has been
							verified by the ARRL.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<table frame='all' xml:id='QslSent'>
				<title>QSL Sent Values and Meanings</title>
				<tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='Values' colwidth='60'/>
					<colspec colname='ADIFValues' colwidth='150'/>
					<colspec colname='Meanings' />
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='Values'>Value</entry>
						<entry namest='ADIFValues'>ADIF QSL_SENT Field Value</entry>
						<entry namest='Meanings'>Meaning</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Yes</entry>
							<entry>Y</entry>
							<entry>An outgoing QSL card has been sent.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>No</entry>
							<entry>N</entry>
							<entry>Do not send an outgoing QSL card.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Requested</entry>
							<entry>R</entry>
							<entry>The contacted station has requested a QSL card.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Queued</entry>
							<entry>Q</entry>
							<entry>An outgoing QSL card has been selected to be sent.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Ignore</entry>
							<entry>I</entry>
							<entry>Ignore this QSO.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<table frame='all' xml:id='QslSentVia'>
				<title>QSL Sent Via Values and Meanings</title>
				<tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='Values' colwidth='60'/>
					<colspec colname='ADIFValues' colwidth='160'/>
					<colspec colname='Meanings' />
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='Values'>Value</entry>
						<entry namest='ADIFValues'>ADIF QSL_SENT_VIA Field Value</entry>
						<entry namest='Meanings'>Meaning</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Bureau</entry>
							<entry>B</entry>
							<entry>An outgoing QSL card should be, or has been, sent via the bureau.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Direct</entry>
							<entry>D</entry>
							<entry>An outgoing QSL card should be, or has been, sent direct to the
							contacted station or his manager.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Electronic</entry>
							<entry>E</entry>
							<entry>The QSO should be, or has been, uploaded to an online service.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Importing QSOs</title>
			<para>The Import QSOs... menu item opens the default ADIF files folder in a File Open 
			dialog to allow the user to select an ADIF file to load QSOs from. The default ADIF files
			folder is set in user preferences. See the
			<link linkend="settinguserprefs">Setting User Preferences</link> chapter for more
			information on setting this default folder.</para>
			<para>ADIF files have the file
			extension <emphasis>.adi</emphasis>. Opening a file deletes any QSOs that had
			previously been loaded and loads the QSOs contained in the file
			into HamQSLer. The QSOs are then displayed in the QSOs View in the QSOs tab. The image below
			shows the main window and QSOs tab when the sample.adi file, located in the Samples
			subdirectory, is loaded.</para>
			<figure xml:id="sampleqsosloaded2">
				<title>Main Program Window With Sample QSOs loaded</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/sampleqsosloaded.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The contents of the QSOs View, the sort panel and the selection panel are discussed
			in another section below.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Adding QSOs</title>
			<para>The Add QSOs... menu item opens the default ADIF files folder in a File Open dialog 
			to allow
			the user to select an ADIF file to load QSOs from. The default ADIF files folder is set
			in the user preferences. See the <link linkend="settinguserprefs">Setting User
			Preferences</link> chapter for more information on this option.</para>
			<para>The QSOs in the ADIF file are added
			to any QSOs that were previously loaded into the program. Once the QSOs have been loaded,
			any duplicated QSOs are deleted, and then the QSOs are sorted according the sort order
			selected in the sort panel.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Clear QSOs</title>
			<para>The Clear QSOs menu item deletes all QSOs that were loaded into HamQSLer.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Exporting QSOs</title>
			<para>The Export QSOs... menu item opens the default ADID files folder in a File Save 
			dialog. This
			allows the user to save any QSOs that are loaded in the program to an ADIF file. Normally
			the user would only want to do this if he input one or more QSOs using the QSO input
			dialog, or if he changed the manager field in the QSOs view.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Reloading ADIF Files on Program Startup</title>
			<para>The Reload ADIF File on Startup setting in user preferences determines whether
			the ADIF files that were loaded before HamQSLer was last terminated are
			reloaded when the program restarts. See <link linkend="settinguserprefs">Setting
			User Preferences</link> for more information on this setting. The list of ADIF files to be
			reloaded is maintained in the user preferences file.</para>
			<para>The following table describes what ADIF files are saved to be reloaded based
			on the actions related to ADIF files.</para>
			<table frame='all'>
				<title>ADIF File List For Reloading - Menu Items and Actions</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='MenuItem' colwidth='70pt'/>
					<colspec colname='Action'/>
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='MenuItem'>Menu Item</entry>
						<entry namest='Action'>Action</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Import QSOs...</entry>
							<entry>The reload list is cleared, and the name of the ADIF file being
							imported is added to the list.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Add QSOs...</entry>
							<entry>The name of the ADIF file being added is added to the list.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Clear QSOs</entry>
							<entry>The reload list is cleared.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Export QSOs...</entry>
							<entry>The reload list is cleared and the name of the ADIF file that is
							saved is added to the list.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<caution>
				<para>The list of files to be reloaded is initialized to an empty list when the
				Reload ADIF Files on Startup setting is changed. Therefore, only the actions performed
				after the setting is set are valid. For example, if you set the Reload ADIF Files
				on Startup setting after loading an ADIF file, that file will not be reloaded the
				next time the program starts.</para>
			</caution>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Sorting and Selecting QSOs</title>
		<section>
			<title>The QSOs Panel</title>
			<figure xml:id="sampleqsosloaded3">
				<title>Main Program Window With Sample QSOs loaded</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/sampleqsosloaded.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The image above shows the main program window with the QSOs tab selected immediately
			after the sample QSOs are loaded. The panel on the left is the QSOs panel, which contains
			a table of some of the fields for each QSO. The following table contains a list of the
			columns in the panel and their contents or meaning.</para>
			<table frame='all'>
				<title>QSOs Panel Columns</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='ColumnHeading' colwidth='85pt'/>
					<colspec colname='ContentsOrMeaning'/>
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='ColumnHeading'>Column Heading</entry>
						<entry namest='ContentsOrMeaning'>Contents or Meaning</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Include</entry>
							<entry>A checkbox indicating whether this QSO will be included when
							cards are printed.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Call</entry>
							<entry>The other station's call sign.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Manager</entry>
							<entry>The call sign of the other station's QSL manager.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Date</entry>
							<entry>The start date of the QSO (or the end date if the start date is
							not specified).</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Time</entry>
							<entry>The start time of the QSO (or the end time if the start time is
							not specified).</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Band</entry>
							<entry>The band that the QSO occurred on, or the band that the other
							station transmitted on.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Freq</entry>
							<entry>The frequency that the other station used for the QSO.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Mode</entry>
							<entry>The mode used for the QSO.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>RST</entry>
							<entry>The signal report you sent to the other station.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Sent</entry>
							<entry>Value corresponding to the ADIF QSL_SENT field. See the 
							<link linkend="QslSent">QSL Sent Values and Meanings</link>
							table in the Inputting QSOs section, above.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Rcvd</entry>
							<entry>Value corresponding to the ADIF QSL_RCVD field. See the
							<link linkend="QslRcvd">QSL Rcvd Values and Meanings</link>
							table in the Input QSOs section, above.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Send Via</entry>
							<entry>Value indicates whether the QSL card containing this QSO should
							be sent via the Bureau or Direct. See the
							<link linkend="QslSentVia">QSL Sent Via Values and Meanings</link>
							table in the Input QSOs section, above.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<para>Values in only the Include and Manager columns are editable. Including
			QSOs when printing cards is discussed in the 
			<link linkend="includingQSOs">Selecting QSOs for Printing</link> section. 
			The Manager fields are
			standard text box fields. All of the standard text editing features are included.</para>
			<para>The QSOs are sorted in one of three ways. This is discussed in the 
			<link linkend='sortingQSOs'>Sorting QSOs</link> section.</para>
		</section>
		<section xml:id='sortingQSOs'>
			<title>Sorting QSOs</title>
			 <para>The image below provides a larger view of the Sort panel
			in the QSOs properties panel.</para>
			<figure xml:id="sort">
				<title>Sort Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/sort.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>With the Date/Time radio button selected, the QSOs are sorted by date and then
			by time. This is the default sort order (the order in which the QSOs are sorted when QSOs
			are first loaded).</para>
			<para>Selecting the Call radio button sorts the QSOs by Manager call sign if one is included
			in the QSO,
			then by the other station's call sign, and then by date and time.</para>
			<para>Selecting the Bureau radio button sorts the QSOs by the bureau for the Manager if
			a Manager is included in the QSO or the bureau for the other station if a Manager is not
			included, then by the Manager callsign, the other station's callsign, and then by
			date and time. The QSOs whose Manager (or call sign field) has a valid bureau are sorted
			first in the list, then the QSOs for which there is no bureau are placed after the bureau
			QSOs. QSOs whose QSL_SENT_VIA ADIF field is set to D (Direct) also have their Send Via
			value set to Direct and are therefore sorted with other Direct QSOs.</para>
			<para>The QSOs are sorted as soon as a radio button is selected. The Sort button is enabled
			only when a new QSO is input using the Input QSOs dialog box. When entering QSOs manually,
			the QSOs are added the bottom of the displayed QSOs. The Sort button must be clicked to
			properly sort the QSOs in that case.</para>
		</section>
		<section xml:id='includingQSOs'>
			<title>Selecting QSOs for Printing</title>
			<para>When you first input, import, or add QSOs, all QSOs are selected.
			There are many ways to select QSOs for printing:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Using filters contained in the filter tabs. You may select QSOs by band,
					mode, QSL statuses and by date and time ranges.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting and deselecting individual QSOs in the QSOs panel.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting and deselecting multiple QSOs in the QSOs panel.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Selecting and deselecting all QSOs.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>Each of these methods is discussed in the subsections below.</para>
			<section>
				<title>Filtering QSOs for Printing</title>
				<para>QSOs may be filtered by band, mode, QSL statuses, and
				by date and time range using the filters in the filters tabs. The image below shows
				the filters tabs with the band tab selected. Each of the filters is discussed in
				the subsections which follow.</para>
				<figure xml:id="qsosfiltertabs">
					<title>Band Filter Tab</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/bandfilter.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<caution>
					<para>The settings in the four filter tabs
					work together to determine whether a QSO will be included
					for printing or not. Even though the individual filter sections state that
					you can include all QSOs that match a particular filter by checking that filter,
					some QSOs may not be included because other filters that affect these QSOs
					may be unchecked.</para>
				</caution>
				<section>
					<title>Filtering QSOs by Band</title>
					<para>The Band filter tab contains a checkbox for each band that is included
					in at least one of the QSOs that is loaded. The image above shows the Band
					tab as it would be with the sample.adi file in the Samples directory loaded.</para>
					<para>Check a band checkbox to include all QSOs made in that band when printing
					cards. Uncheck a band checkbox to not include those QSOs.</para>
					<tip>
						<para>You may override the Include checkbox for individual QSOs after this
						filter has been set. See the 
						<link linkend="manuallyselectingqsos">Selecting Individual QSOs</link>
						section for more information.</para>
					</tip>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Filtering QSOs by Mode</title>
					<para>The Mode filter tab contains a checkbox for each mode that is included
					in at least one of the QSOs that is loaded. The image below shows the Mode
					tab as it would be with the sample.adi file in the Samples directory loaded.</para>
					<figure xml:id="modefilter">
						<title>Mode Filter Tab</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="images/modefilter.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					<para>Check a mode checkbox to include all QSOs made in that mode when printing
					cards. Uncheck a mode checkbox to not include those QSOs.</para>
					<tip>
						<para>You may override the Include checkbox for individual QSOs after this
						filter has been set. See the 
						<link linkend="manuallyselectingqsos">Manually Selecting QSOs</link>
						section for more information.</para>
					</tip>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Filtering QSOs by QSL Statuses</title>
					<para>The QSL Status filter tab contains panels for QSL received status,
					QSL sent status and Send Via status. Each panel contains a checkbox for each
					status that is included in at least one loaded QSO. The image below shows
					the QSL Status tab as it would be with the sample.adi file in the Samples
					directory loaded.</para>
					<figure xml:id="qslstatusfilter">
						<title>QSL Status Filter Tab</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="images/qslstatusfilter.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					<para>Check a status checkbox to include all QSOs containing that status
					when printing cards. Uncheck a status checkbox to not include those QSOs.</para>
					<tip>
						<para>You may override the Include checkbox for individual QSOs after this
						filter has been set. See the 
						<link linkend="manuallyselectingqsos">Manually Selecting QSOs</link>
						section for more information.</para>
					</tip>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Filtering QSOs by Date and Time</title>
					<para>The Date/Time filter tab contains a start date and time and an end date
					and time as well as a Reset button. The image below shows the Date/Time filter
					tab as it would be immediately after loading the sample.adi file located in
					the Samples directory.</para>
					<figure xml:id="datetimefilter">
						<title>Date/Time Filter Tab</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="images/datetimefilter.png" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</figure>
					<para>When QSOs are first loaded, the values in the start date and time 
					text boxes correspond to date and time of the earliest QSO that is loaded.
					The values in the end date and time text boxes correspond to the date and
					time of the latest QSO that is loaded.</para>
					<para>To select QSOs over a narrower date and time range, change the dates and
					times to the range that you want. The Include checkbox for all QSOs that are 
					outside this range will be unchecked.</para>
					<para>Click the Reset button to reset the start and end dates and times to the
					earliest and latest dates and times for the loaded QSOs.</para>
					<caution>
						<para>The entered dates and times must be between 19451101 and the current
						date and time.</para>
					</caution>
					<tip>
						<para>You may override the Include checkbox for individual QSOs after this
						filter has been set. See the 
						<link linkend="manuallyselectingqsos">Manually Selecting QSOs</link>
						section for more information.</para>
					</tip>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section xml:id='manuallyselectingqsos'>
				<title>Manually Selecting QSOs For Printing</title>
				<para>Individual QSOs may be selected or deselected for printing by checking or
				unchecking the checkbox in the Include column corresponding to the QSO that you
				want to include or not include.</para>
				<para>The Include status of multiple QSOs may be set by first selecting all of the
				QSOs whose status you want to change, and then checking or unchecking the Include
				checkbox for one of the selected QSOs. To select a number of QSOs, you must start by
				selecting one QSO. Do this by clicking anywhere in the QSO in the QSOs panel except
				in the Include checkbox or the Manager text box. The QSO will be highlighted. The
				image below shows the QSO with CG3JNO selected.</para>
				<figure xml:id="qsoselected">
					<title>QSO With CG3JNO Selected</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/qsoselected.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>To select additional QSOs, press and hold the Ctrl key, then click on each
				QSO that you want to select. Each selected QSO will be highlighted. When you have
				selected all of the wanted QSOs, release the Ctrl button.</para>
				<para>To select a range of QSOs, select the first QSO in the range. Press the Shift
				key and click on the last QSO in the range that you want to select, then release the
				Shift key. All QSOs in the range will be highlighted. You may then select additional
				QSOs by pressing the Ctrl key before clicking on those QSOs.</para>
				<para>To change the Include checkboxes for all selected QSOs, check or uncheck
				the Include checkbox for one of the selected QSOs. The Include checkboxes for all
				selected QSOs will be changed to match the new state and the QSOs will be 
				deselected.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>If the Include checkboxes for some of the selected QSOs are checked and
					some are unchecked, the final state will match the toggled state of the checkbox
					that you click. That is, if the checkbox that you clicked was checked when
					you clicked it, then the checkboxes for all selected QSOs will be unchecked.</para>
				</caution>
				<para>You may select all QSOs by first clicking anywhere within the QSOs panel and
				then pressing the Ctrl and A keys on the keyboard or by selecting the Select
				All QSOs menu item in the Select dropdown menu. You may deselect any selected
				QSOs by selecting the Deselect All QSOs menu item in the Select dropdown 
				menu.</para>
				<para>And lastly, you may check all Include checkboxes by selecting the
				Include All QSOs menu item in the QSOs dropdown menu, and you may uncheck
				all Include checkboxes by selecting the Exclude All QSOs menu item in the
				QSOs dropdown menu.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>If you change any of the filters after you have manually selected QSOs,
					all of your manual selections are lost. You will have to set them again.</para>
				</caution>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
