<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="workingwithqsos">
	<title>Working With QSOs</title>
	<para>The majority of HamQSLer users make use of a QSO logging program; logging programs
	vary in functionality from simple, basically equivalent to a computerized paper log, up
	to complex programs that track awards, monitor and control transmitters and receivers, 
	interact with digital modems, and communicate with electronic QSLing services such as 
	Logbook of the World
	and eQSL. The one common component that exists in all modern logging programs is the
	ability to exchange data with other programs using Amateur Data Interchange Format (ADIF).</para>
	<para>The ADIF standard has existed for many years, and has gone through many changes over
	that time. The standard is very flexible in that it specifies the various fields that can
	be contained in a QSO record, but does not mandate that all or even a specific subset of the fields
	is required in every record. The one requirement that ADIF makes for any program that claims
	compatibility with any version of the standard is that it must accept as input ADIF files that were
	generated to any version of the ADIF standard that preceeds the standard that the receiving program
	claims compatibility with.</para>
	<caution>
		<para>HamQSLer attempts to follow the ADIF standard but in a few places does not. In general,
		this does not cause a problem because HamQSLer is only interested in a few of the fields
		that appear in QSO records in an ADIF file. Compatibility with the latest ADIF standard is
		one of the first sets of changes that will be made to HamQSLer once it has been released.</para>
	</caution>
	<caution>
		<para>HamQSLer validates QSO records to ensure that they contain at least a minimum set of
		data: start or end date and time for the QSO, frequency or band used, mode used for the QSO,
		and the callsign of the station contacted. A number of validity checks are performed on the
		data that is input via ADIF. For example, if a frequency is specified, it must be within
		the ADIF specified ham bands, and the callsign must be valid. More information on the checking
		that HamQSLer does to each QSO record being input is provided in the Importing QSOs section,
		below.</para>
	</caution>
	<para>A number of users may still keep paper logs. HamQSLer provides a dialog for manually inputting
	QSOs one at a time. This facility may be used as the only means of inputting QSOs, or may be
	used in addition to loading QSO data from ADIF files.</para>
	<para>This chapter discusses importing QSO data from ADIF files, inputting QSOs using the input
	dialog, sorting the QSOs and selecting QSOs to be printed on QSL cards.</para>
</chapter>
