<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="carddesign">
	<title>Working With Cards</title>
	<section>
		<title>Saving HamQSLer Card Files</title>
		<para>Once a card has been created, it may be saved to be loaded
		and used at a future time. To do this, select the Cards->File Save or
		Cards->File Save As... menu items. File Save is only available if the
		card has previously been saved because the program must know the
		directory in which you want to save the card.</para>
		<para>When you select the Card Save As... menu item, the File Save
		dialog, shown below, is displayed.</para>
		<figure xml:id="savecarddialog2">
			<title>File Save Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/savecarddialog.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The dialog opens with the default directory set to your hamqsler
		folder. Navigate to the folder where you want to save the card file,
		then click on the Save button. The card file will be saved and the
		dialog will close.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Loading HamQSLer Card Files</title>
		<para>Once a card has been saved, it can be loaded at a later time
		by selecting the Cards->Open Card... menu item. This displays the
		File Open dialog with the default directory set to your hamqsler
		folder. See the image below:</para>
		<figure xml:id="cardopendialog">
			<title>File Open Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/cardopendialog.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The dropdown box circled in red near the bottom right of the
		dialog lets you select the type of card to open. It defaults to
		HamQSLer cards, which have an extension of ".qslx".</para>
		<para>Navigate to the directory containing the card file you want
		to open, and either click on the file and then the Open button,
		or double-click on the file.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>Keep all of your card related files (card files, images,
			logos, etc.) in the hamqsler directory or create subdirectories
			for each file type. That way, all of the files needed for
			your cards are located in one place so they are easy to back
			up and to move to another location.</para>
			<para>In the past, as Microsoft released new versions of Windows,
			they sometimes changed the location of the My Directories folder.
			This occurred, for example, when Windows Vista was released,
			and people who upgraded from Windows XP had problems with hard-coded 
			paths.</para>
		</tip>
		<tip>
			<para>If you want to reload the saved card or cards every time
			you restart the program, check the "Reload Card Files on Startup"
			checkbox in the User Preferences. See the <link linkend="settinguserprefs">
			User Preferences</link> chapter for more information.</para>
		</tip>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Loading QslDesignAndPrint Card Files</title>
		<para>Card files that were created with QslDesignAndPrint may be
		loaded into HamQSLer. To do this, select the Cards->Open Card...
		menu item. Then select the QslDnP Card type from the dropdown
		box circled in red in the figure above.</para>
		<para>Navigate to the directory containing the card file you want
		to open, and either click on the file and then the Open button,
		or double-click on the file.</para>
		<caution>
			<para>This feature is deprecated and will be removed in the
			future. Load all of your QslDesignAndPrint cards
			into HamQSLer and then save them using the Cards->Save As...
			menu item. Be sure to save the new cards in the hamqsler folder.</para>
		</caution>
		<caution>
			<para>When you load a QslDesignAndPrint card into HamQSLer,
			the program marks the card as modified. If you attempt to close
			the program before you have saved the card, you will get a
			message asking if you want to save the file. If you answer
			Yes, then the file is saved in the same directory as the card
			file was loaded from. You are not given the option of saving
			the file in a different directory.</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
</chapter>
