<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
		 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 xml:id="carddesign">
	<title>Working With Cards</title>
	<section>
		<title>Saving HamQSLer Card Files</title>
		<para>Once a card has been created, it may be saved to be loaded
		and used at a future time. To do this, select the Cards => File Save or
		Cards => File Save As... menu items. File Save is only available if the
		card has previously been saved because the program must know the
		directory in which you want to save the card.</para>
		<para>When you select the Card Save As... menu item, the File Save As
		dialog, shown below, is displayed.</para>
		<figure xml:id="savecarddialog2">
			<title>File Save As Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/savecarddialog.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The dialog opens in the default card files folder. This folder can
		be set in user preferences. See 
		<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting
		User Preferences</emphasis></link> for setting this value. 
		Navigate to the folder where you want to save the card file,
		enter the name you want to save the file as, and
		then click on the Save button. The card file will be saved and the
		dialog will close.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Loading HamQSLer Card Files</title>
		<para>Once a card has been saved, it can be loaded at a later time
		by selecting the Cards => Open Card... menu item. This displays the
		File Open dialog with the default directory set to the default card files
		folder. See the image below:</para>
		<figure xml:id="cardopendialog">
			<title>File Open Dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/cardopendialog.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		
		<para>Navigate to the directory containing the card file you want
		to open, and either click on the file and then the Open button,
		or double-click on the file.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>Keep all of your card related files (card files, images,
			logos, etc.) in the <filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename>
			directory or create subdirectories
			for each file type. That way, all of the files needed for
			your cards are located in one place so they are easy to back
			up and to move to another location.</para>
			<para>In the past, as Microsoft released new versions of Windows,
			they sometimes changed the location of the 
			<filename class='directory'>My Directories</filename> folder.
			This occurred, for example, when Windows Vista was released,
			and people who upgraded from Windows XP ore earlier had problems 
			with hard-coded paths.</para>
		</tip>
		<tip>
			<para>If you want to reload the saved card or cards every time
			you restart the program, check the "Reload Card Files on Startup"
			checkbox in the User Preferences. See the 
			<link linkend="settinguserprefs"><emphasis role='undlerline'>User 
			Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter for more information.</para>
		</tip>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Moving and Converting QslDesignAndPrint Files</title>
		<para>QslDesignAndPrint card files are normally stored in the
		<filename role='underline'>QslDnP</filename> subdirectory of your 
		<filename role='underline'>My Documents</filename> directory.
		You may also
		have stored other related files such as images, logos, and
		possibly ADIF files in <filename class='directory'>QslDnP</filename>.</para>
		<para> 
		<literal>HamQSLer</literal> uses the <filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename> 
		subdirectory in <filename class='directory'>My Documents</filename>. 
		To ease the transition from <literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal> to
		<literal>HamQSLer</literal>, a move and convert tool has been included in 
		<literal>HamQSLer</literal>. 
		This tool performs two tasks:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>All files except log files, card files, and the user preferences
				file are copied from
				a user selected source directory to a user specified destination directory. 
				These files have the extensions <filename>.xqsl</filename>, 
				<filename>.xml</filename>, <filename>.log</filename>, 
				and <filename>.log-old</filename>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Card files are converted from <literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal> 
				format to
				<literal>HamQSLer</literal> format and copied to the 
				destination directory and its subdirectories.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>The following files are not copied or converted: 
		<filename>...\Samples\text2.adi</filename>,
		<filename>...\Samples\moonbasin.jpg</filename>, and 
		<filename>...\Samples\sample.xqsl</filename>. These three files are
		used in the <literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal> getting started tutorial; 
		a different set of files is used in the <literal>HamQSLer</literal>
		getting started tutorial.</para>
		<para>To copy and convert your <literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal> related files, 
		select
		the Tools => Import QslDesignAndPrint Files menu item. This opens a Browse For
		Folder dialog. Select the directory containing the files you want to copy and
		convert, then click the OK button. Another Browse For Folder dialog will open;
		use this dialog to select the destination directory, and click the OK button.
		Copying and conversion will begin.</para>
		<para>If one or more errors occurs when copying files from the source directory
		to the destination directory,
		the following message box will be displayed, and as noted, the file or files
		that could not be copied are listed in the log file along with the reason why.</para>
		<figure xml:id="qsldnpfilecopyerrorbox">
			<title>Copy Error Message Box</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/qsldnpcopyerrorbox.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>If no files were copied, either because the source directory was empty,
		or because the files in the directory had already been copied to the destination
		directory, the message box shown below is displayed.</para>
		<figure xml:id="nofilescopied">
			<title>No Files Copied Message Box</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/nofilescopied.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>If the source directory contains no card files, or if there were errors
		detected while converting every card file, then the following message box is
		displayed as a warning.</para>
		<figure xml:id="nocardscoverted">
			<title>No Cards Converted Message Box</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/nocardsconverted.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>If an image in a <literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal>
		card file references an image
		file in the source directory, then the location of the image
		file is changed to the destination directory. If any image file cannot be located, 
		then the message box shown below is displayed, and you are given the choice
		between trying to locate the file yourself or deleting the image.</para>
		<figure xml:id="imagefilenotfoundbox">
			<title>Image File Not Found Message Box</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/imagefilenotfoundbox.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>If a font cannot be located, it is replaced by the first font in the
		installed fonts list. See the caution below related to fonts.</para>
		<para>When all files have been moved and all card files have been converted,
		the text "Files have been copied and card files converted. See log file for
		details." is
		displayed in the status bar at the bottom of <literal>HamQSLer</literal>'s 
		main window. The log
		file contains a message for every file copied, every card file converted, every
		image replaced, every font that could not be found, and every error that was
		detected during the copy and conversion tasks.</para>
		<caution>
			<para><literal>HamQSLer</literal> uses a different graphical user interface than 
			<literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal> to draw cards. In some cases, font face names are
			different; if your card file references one of these font face names,
			then the card will not display text in your selected font. The font will
			be replaced by the first font in the installed fonts list. You may of course 
			change the font face at any time while the card is in design mode.</para>
			<para><literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal> used Windows Presentation Foundation (WPF) to
			print and display cards. <literal>HamQSLer</literal> uses Windows Forms libraries for
			printing and displaying cards. There are two potential differences between
			these libraries as related to fonts:</para>
			<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
				<listitem>
					<para>WPF enumerates all fonts that are installed on your computer.
					Windows forms only enumerates installed fonts that are located in
					your <filename class='directory'>...\Windows\Fonts</filename> directory.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>There may be small differences in names between the list of
					installed fonts returned by WPF and by Windows Forms. This only
					affects a few font names.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>For these reasons, one or more of the fonts on your 
			<literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal>
			cards may be replaced by the first font in the Windows Forms installed fonts
			list during the conversion process.</para>
		</caution>
		<caution>
			<para><literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal> supports three font weights: 
			<emphasis>normal</emphasis>, <emphasis>bold</emphasis>, 
			and <emphasis>black</emphasis>.
			<literal>HamQSLer</literal> only supports <emphasis>normal</emphasis> and 
			<emphasis>bold</emphasis>. For most font faces used in
			<literal>QslDesignAndPrint</literal>, <emphasis>black</emphasis> is simply displayed as 
			<emphasis>bold</emphasis>. The one obvious
			font face for which there is a <emphasis>black</emphasis> font weight is Arial.
			</para>
			<para>An Arial Black font is available on the Internet, but it does not
			look like Arial with a font weight of black. An alternative to Arial Black
			is Helvetica Black.  You may purchase Helvetica fonts, but they
			are not available free of charge, and will only be available on your
			computer if another application has loaded them.</para>
			<para>An alternative font face with thicker characters is Verdana, although
			character shapes are different from Arial.</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Creating a New Card</title>
		<para>A new card may be created by selecting the Cards => New menu item. This
		opens another submenu from which to select the card size and orientation that
		you want. At this time, there are three card sizes available:</para>
		<itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Bureau sized card in landscape mode (5.5 inches wide by 3.5 inches high,
				or 139.7 mm wide by 88.9 mm high). This is the standard size for QSL cards
				and is the size preferred by all QSL bureaus. There are three known suppliers
				of perforated cardstock for this size of card. See the
				<link linkend='outputtingcards'><emphasis role='underline'>Outputting
				Cards</emphasis></link> chapter for more
				information.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>5.5 inches wide by 4.25 inches wide in landscape mode (139.7 mm wide by
				107.95 mm high). Four of these cards may be printed in a two by two layout
				on US Letter sized card stock. A number of micro-perforated cardstocks are
				available in this size. See the
				<link linkend='outputtingcards'><emphasis role='underline'>Outputting
				Cards</emphasis></link> chapter for more
				information.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>6 inches wide by 4 inches high in landscape mode (152.4 mm wide by
				101.6 mm high). This corresponds to standard 4 inch by 6 inch or 10 cm by
				15 cm photopaper.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Select the menu item for the card size that you want. 
		The new card will be displayed in a new
		tab in the main window; this tab displays the card in design mode in the panel
		on the left, and a properties panel on the right. If you set up the various text 
		items properties in User Preferences, as outlined in the 
		<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User 
		Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter,
		then a card similar to the image below will be displayed. The card in this image is
		bureau sized. If you select a different size card, then that size of card is
		displayed.</para>
		<figure xml:id="newcard2">
			<title>New Bureau Sized Card When First Created</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/newcard.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The tab header contains the text "New Card" and the window title is "HamQSLer -
		New Card". Once you have changed one of the card properties, the tab header will change
		to "*New Card", and the window title will change to "HamQSLer - New Card - Modified"
		to show that one or more changes have been made to the card. When you save the card,
		the tab header will contain the name of the file that you saved the card to, and the
		window title will contain "HamQSLer - <emphasis>full path to card file</emphasis>.</para>
		<para>Again when you modify the card further, an asterisk ("*") will be prepended to the 
		tab header, and " - Modified" will be appended to the window title.</para>
		<para>The properties panel on the right side of the card tab contains default printer and
		print properties for the card, or card item specific properties when a card item is
		selected. Card default printer and print properties are discussed in the
		<link linkend='outputtingcards'><emphasis role='underline'>Outputting
		Cards</emphasis></link> chapter and therefore
		will not be mentioned further here.</para>
		<para>Cards that are designed using HamQSLer may contain:</para>
		<itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>A background image.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Any number of secondary images.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Any number of text items.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Zero or one Qsos Box which contains QSO information.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>A new card contains no background or secondary images; three text items:
		callsign, name and QTH, and a salutation; and a Qsos Box. Any item on a card may be
		deleted from the card, and any item may be added to the card. Background image is a
		special case. The actual image may be cleared, but the background image item is still
		maintained as an item on the card. The Qsos Box is also a special case. Only one
		Qsos Box is permitted on a card, so it is only possible to add a Qsos Box if the
		original Qsos Box has been deleted.</para>
		<para>The following sections deal with the properties of each card item type, but
		first we will discuss card design related menu items and then highlighting and 
		selecting card items.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Card Design Related Menus and Menu Items</title>
		<section>
			<title>Card Design Context Menu</title>
			<para>The card design context menu, shown below, is displayed by clicking the right
			mouse button anywhere within the card design panel. The menu items that are enabled
			and disabled are determined by the placement of the cursor when the mouse button
			was clicked and on a number of design conditions. For example, the Clear Background
			Image menu item is only enabled if there is a background image.</para>
			<figure xml:id="carddesigncontextmenu">
				<title>Card Design Context Menu</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/carddesigncontextmenu.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>This table shows the menu items and their actions.</para>
			<table frame='all'>
				<title>Card Design Context Menu Items and Actions</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='MenuItem' colwidth='125pt'/>
					<colspec colname='Action'/>
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='MenuItem'>Menu Item</entry>
						<entry namest='Action'>Action</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Select Highlighted Item</entry>
							<entry>Selects the highlighted card item to allow editing of the
							item's properties. See 
							<link linkend='highlightingitems'><emphasis role='underline'>Highlighting
							and Selecting Card Items</emphasis></link> for more 
							information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Deselect Item</entry>
							<entry>Deselects the selected card item. See 
							<link linkend='highlightingitems'><emphasis role='underline'>Highlighting 
							and Selecting Card Items</emphasis></link> for more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Add Image</entry>
							<entry>Adds a new secondary image to the card and selects it
							for editing. See 
							<link linkend='addingimages'><emphasis role='underline'>Adding
							Secondary Images</emphasis></link> for more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Add Text Item</entry>
							<entry>Adds a new text item to the card. See
							<link linkend='addingtextitems'><emphasis role='underline'>Adding 
							New Text Items</emphasis></link> for
							more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Add Qsos Box</entry>
							<entry>Adds a new Qsos Box to the card. See
							<link linkend='addingqsosbox'><emphasis role='underline'>Adding 
							a Qsos Box</emphasis></link> for
							more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Delete Selected Item</entry>
							<entry>Deletes the selected card item from the card. See
							<link linkend='deletingitem'><emphasis role='underline'>Deleting 
							a Card Item</emphasis></link> for more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Clear Background Image</entry>
							<entry>Clears the background image. See
							<link linkend='clearbackground'><emphasis role='underline'>Clearing 
							the Background Image</emphasis></link> for more information.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Edit Dropdown Menu</title>
			<figure xml:id="editmenu">
				<title>Edit Dropdown Menu</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/editmenu.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The image above shows the open Edit dropdown menu. The table shows the 
			card design related menu items and their actions.</para>
			<table frame='all'>
				<title>Card Design Related Edit Dropdown Menu Items and Actions</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='MenuItem' colwidth='125pt'/>
					<colspec colname='Action'/>
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='MenuItem'>Menu Item</entry>
						<entry namest='Action'>Action</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Add Image</entry>
							<entry>Adds a new secondary image to the card and selects it
							for editing. See
							<link linkend='addingimages'><emphasis role='underline'>Adding 
							Secondary Images</emphasis></link> for more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Add Text Item</entry>
							<entry>Adds a new text item to the card. See
							<link linkend='addingtextitems'><emphasis role='underline'>Adding 
							New Text Items</emphasis></link> for
							more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Add Qsos Box</entry>
							<entry>Adds a new Qsos Box to the card. See
							<link linkend='addingqsosbox'><emphasis role='underline'>Adding 
							a Qsos Box</emphasis></link> for
							more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Delete Selected Item</entry>
							<entry>Deletes the selected card item from the card. See
							<link linkend='deletingitem'><emphasis role='underline'>Deleting 
							a Card Item</emphasis></link>
							for more information.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Clear Background Image</entry>
							<entry>Clears the background image. See
							<link linkend='clearbackground'><emphasis role='underline'>Clearing 
							the Background Image</emphasis></link> for more information.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
		<section xml:id='selectmenu2'>
			<title>Select Dropdown Menu</title>
			<para>The image below shows a sample dropdown menu. The contents of the menu
			above the separator (the line) changes depending on image and text item properties.
			For example, the first item in the menu is "Background" if there
			is no background image, and the file name of the background image if there is
			one. Similarly, each secondary image has a menu item: "Image" if
			there is no image loaded, and the file name of the image if there is one loaded.
			Menu items for each text item contains the first 10 characters of the design text
			for the text item.</para>
			<figure xml:id="sampleselectmenu">
				<title>Sample Select Dropdown Menu</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/sampleselectmenu.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The following table shows the menu items and their actions. See
			<link linkend='highlightingitems'><emphasis role='underline'>Highlighting 
			and Selecting Card Items</emphasis></link>
			for more information on selecting card items.</para>
			<table frame='all'>
				<title>Card Design Related Select Dropdown Menu Items and Actions</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
					<colspec colname='MenuItem' colwidth='125pt'/>
					<colspec colname='Action'/>
					<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest='MenuItem'>Menu Item</entry>
						<entry namest='Action'>Action</entry>
					</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Background</entry>
							<entry>Selects the background image. This menu item only
							appears when there is no image specified for the background.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Image</entry>
							<entry>Selects the secondary image. This menu item only
							appears for secondary images that do not have an image file
							specified.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>image file name</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>Selects the background or secondary image item that
							has this file name specified.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>text</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>Selects the text item whose design text starts with
							this text.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Qsos Box</entry>
							<entry>Selects the Qsos Box card item. This menu item only appears
							if there is a Qsos Box on the card.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>None</entry>
							<entry>Deselects the selected card item.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section xml:id='highlightingitems'>
		<title>Highlighting and Selecting Card Items</title>
		<para>When you move the mouse cursor over any card item on the card, that card item
		is highlighted or outlined with an orange dashed line. For example, the image below
		shows the salutation text item highlighted because the mouse cursor is over it.</para>
		<figure xml:id="highlighteditem">
			<title>Salutation Text Item Highlighted</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/highlighteditem.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>As mentioned earlier, the background image is a special card item. If there
		is a background image on the card, that image is highlighted when the cursor moves
		over it; if there is no background image present, then the card is outlined. This is
		done so that you know there is no background image for the card and so that the
		background may be selected.</para>
		<para>Card items may overlap. When you move the mouse cursor over the area where these
		card items overlap, the card item with higher precedence is highlighted. The list below
		shows the precedence of card items from highest to lowest:</para>
		<simplelist>
			<member>Qsos Box.</member>
			<member>Text items in the reverse of the order that they were created.</member>
			<member>Secondary images in the reverse of the order that they were created.
			</member>
			<member>Background.</member>
		</simplelist>
		<para>A card item may be selected in one of two ways:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Move the cursor over the card item to highlight it, then click the right
				mouse button to open the card item context menu. Select the "Select Highlighted
				Item" menu item from the context menu. The contents of this context menu is
				discussed in the 
				<link linkend='carddesigncontextmenu'><emphasis role='underline'>Card Design
				Context Menu</emphasis></link> section, above.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select the card item from the Select dropdown menu. More information
				about this menu is provided in the 
				<link linkend='selectmenu2'><emphasis role='underline'>Select Dropdown
				Menu</emphasis></link> section, above.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>When a card item has been selected, the card item is outlined by a dark blue
		dashed outline, and the properties for the card item are displayed in the card
		properties panel. Editing of card item properties is discussed in a number of sections
		that follow.</para>
		<para>The image below shows the salutation text item that was highlighted in the image
		above once the item has been selected.</para>
		<figure xml:id="selecteditem">
			<title>Salutation Text Item Selected</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/selecteditem.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Deselecting Selected Card Items</title>
		<para>A card item may be deselected in either of the following ways:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Open the card item context menu and select the "Deselect Item"
				menu item.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select the "None" menu item from the Select dropdown menu.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>When the card item is deselected, it is no longer highlighted by a dark
		blue dashed line.</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id='deletingitem'>
		<title>Deleting a Card Item</title>
		<para>A card item must be selected before it can be deleted. There are two ways to delete
		a card item:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select the "Delete Selected Item" menu item from the card items context
				menu.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Delete Selected Item" from the Edit dropdown menu.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<caution>
			<para>Once a card item has been deleted, it cannot be restored; your only option is
			to add a card item (secondary image, text item, or Qsos Box) to the card and modify
			its properties to match the old card item.</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
	<section xml:id='addingimages'>
		<title>Adding Secondary Images</title>
		<para>A secondary image may be added to a card in either of the following ways:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Add Image" from the card items context menu.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Add Image" from the Edit dropdown menu.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>The new secondary image item is initially created as a 1 inch by 1 inch (25.4 mm
		by 25.4 mm) square that is centered on the card. This card item is selected, and
		the secondary image properties panel is displayed in the card properties panel to the
		right of the card design panel. This card item may be moved and resized at any time.
		 See the
		<link linkend='movingcarditem'><emphasis role='underline'>Moving and Resizing Card 
		Items</emphasis></link> section below.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>If your card does not contain a background image, use the background image
			item for the first image on your card. This reduces the size of the card file
			and improves program performance during display and printing operations.</para>
		</tip>
		<caution>
			<para>As stated, when a new secondary image is added to a card, it is centered on
			the card. Because of the order in which card items are drawn (see the precedence
			order in 
			<link linkend='highlightingitems'><emphasis role='underline'>Highlighting and 
			Selecting Card Items</emphasis></link>, above), the image may not be visible. 
			Move any other images, text
			items, and the Qsos Box to see the image.</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
	<section xml:id='addingtextitems'>
		<title>Adding New Text Items</title>
		<para>A new text item may be added to a card in the following ways:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Add Text Item" from the card item context menu.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Add Text Item" from the Edit dropdown menu.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>The new text item is initially positioned with the top left corner of the card
		item located at the center of the card. The text item has the following properties
		when it is created:</para>
		<itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Text is "Text Item".</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Font face is the default text font face that was defined when the
				card was first created. See the 
				<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting
				User Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter for information on setting this 
				default property.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The font size is 12 points.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The text item may be moved at any time. See the
		<link linkend='movingcarditem'><emphasis role='underline'>Moving and Resizing Card 
		Items</emphasis></link> section below.</para>
		<para>When the text item is created, it is automatically selected and the text item
		properties panel is displayed in the card properties panel.</para>
		<caution>
			<para>As stated, when a new text item is added to a card, it is positioned at the
			center of
			the card. Because of the order in which card items are drawn (see the precedence
			order in <link linkend='highlightingitems'><emphasis role='underline'>Highlighting 
			and Selecting Card
			Items</emphasis></link>, above), the text item may not be visible. Move any text
			items and the Qsos Box to see the new text item.</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
	<section xml:id='addingqsosbox'>
		<title>Adding a Qsos Box</title>
		<para>A Qsos Box can be added to a card if the original Qsos Box was deleted. There
		are two ways to add a Qsos Box to a card:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Add Qsos Box" from the card items context menu.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Add Qsos Box" from the Edit dropdown menu.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>The Qsos Box is initially positioned with its upper edge at the center of the
		card. The box width is set at 90% of the width of the card, and the box is positioned
		horizontally at the center of the card. The Qsos Box may be moved and resized at any
		time. See the
		<link linkend='movingcarditem'><emphasis role='underline'>Moving and Resizing Card 
		Items</emphasis></link> section below.</para>
		<para>When the Qsos Box is added to the card, it is selected and the Qsos Box
		properties panel is displayed in the card properties panel.</para>
		<tip>
			<para>Text in the Qsos Box is intially displayed in the Qsos Box default font
			face. See the 
			<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User 
			Preferences</emphasis></link>
			chapter for information on changing this property.</para>
		</tip>
		<tip>
			<para>Text that is displayed in the Qsos Box (confirming text, column headers, and
			the text printed in the QSL column) is defined in the user preferences. See the
			<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User 
			Preferences</emphasis></link>
			chapter for information on setting these text values.</para>
		</tip>
		<caution>
			<para>When a new card is created, the confirming text, column headers, and
			the text that is printed in the QSL column, are copied from the user preferences
			file to the card file. This text remains fixed for this card.</para>
		</caution>
	</section>
	<section xml:id='clearbackground'>
		<title>Clearing the Background Image</title>
		<para>The background image may be cleared in one of two ways:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Clear Background Image" from the card items context menu.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select "Clear Background Image" from the Edit dropdown menu.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>If the background image item was selected before the image was cleared, the item
		remains selected; otherwise it remains unselected.</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id='movingcarditem'>
		<title>Moving and Resizing Card Items</title>
		<para>Once a card item has been selected, it may be moved or resized. All card items
		may be moved using the mouse cursor. Images may also be
		resized using the mouse cursor. Text items may only be resized by changing the text,
		font, font size, and bold and italic properties of the text items. The width of the
		Qsos Box may be changed using the mouse, but its height and its minimum width are
		determined by a number of Qsos Box properties including the font, the font size,
		the columns shown, the column headers, the date format selected, and the maximum
		number of Qsos that may be printed on the card.  See the 
		<link linkend='qsosboxprops'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting Qsos Box 
		Properties</emphasis></link> section for information 
		on changing these properties.</para>
		<para>When the mouse cursor is moved over a selected card item, the cursor will change
		to one of the cursors shown in the table below. The cursor that is displayed is
		determined by the position of the cursor in the card item and the type of card item
		that is selected. To move or resize a card item, press and hold the left mouse button 
		and drag
		the mouse to move the cursor to a new location. Release the mouse button to complete
		the operation. The card item will move or be resized
		as the the mouse is dragged.</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>Move and Resize Mouse Cursors</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
				<colspec colwidth='50' align='center' colname='Cursor' />
				<colspec colname='Action'/>
				<thead>
				<row>
					<entry namest='Cursor'>Cursor</entry>
					<entry namest='Action'>Action</entry>
				</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinemediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/movecursor.png" align="center" />
								</imageobject>
							</inlinemediaobject>
						</entry>
						<entry>This is the move cursor. It is displayed for all card items
						when the mouse cursor is inside the selected card item. Press and hold
						the left
						mouse button and drag the mouse to move the card item. The card item
						moves in the direction and the amount that the mouse cursor is 
						dragged. Release the left mouse button when the card item is positioned
						where you want it.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinemediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/nwse.png" align="center" />
								</imageobject>
							</inlinemediaobject>
						</entry>
						<entry>This cursor is only displayed when the mouse cursor is moved over
						the top left or bottom right corner of a selected background or
						secondary image. Press and hold the left mouse button and drag the mouse
						towards the center of the image to reduce the size of the image. To enlarge
						the image, press the left mouse button and drag the mouse away from
						the center of the image. Release the left mouse button when the
						resize operation is completed. The
						opposite corner of the image remains in a fixed position. The aspect
						ratio (the ratio of image width to image height) of the image
						is not changed.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinemediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/nesw.png" align="center" />
								</imageobject>
							</inlinemediaobject>
						</entry>
						<entry>This cursor is only displayed when the mouse cursor is moved
						over the top right or bottom left corner of a selected background
						or secondary image. Press and hold the left mouse button and drag the
						cursor towards the center of the image to decrease the size of the
						image. Move the mouse cursor away from the center of the image to
						enlarge the image. Release the left mouse button when the
						resize operation is complete. The opposite corner of the image 
						remains fixed. The aspect ratio of the image is not changed.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<inlinemediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/ewcursor.png" align="center" />
								</imageobject>
							</inlinemediaobject>
						</entry>
						<entry>This cursor is only displayed when the mouse cursor is moved
						over the left or right edges of the Qsos Box. Press and hold the left
						mouse button and drag the mouse to the left or right to change the
						width of the Qsos Box. Release the left mouse button when the Qsos Box
						resize operation is complete. The Qsos Box width may be reduced until
						it reaches its minimum size after which further mouse movements are
						ignored.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Setting Card Item Properties</title>
		<para>The methods for setting some card item properties are common between two or
		more card item types. For example, the method used to specify the image file to
		load for background and secondary images is the same. Similarly, the method for setting
		the color of a text item is the same as setting the color of the Qsos Box. These
		common methods are discussed here before the setting of specific card item properties
		is discussed.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Common Properties Methods</title>
			<section xml:id='imagefilename'>
				<title>Setting an Image File Name</title>
				<para>This method is common between background images and secondary images.
				Setting the image file name for the background image of a card will be
				used as the example here.</para>
				<para>The image below shows the background image properties panel. This panel is
				displayed in the card items properties panel when the background image item is
				selected.</para>
				<figure xml:id="backgroundimageproperties2">
					<title>Background Image Properties</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/backgroundimageproperties.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>This image shows the background image properties panel when there is no
				image. To load an image, click the button labeled "...". This displays
				the File Open dialog in the default images folder. Navigate to the directory containing
				the image that you want to use as the card background and select the image. The
				dialog will close and the image will display centered on the card. The initial size
				and position of the image depends on whether you are loading a background image
				or a secondary image. The location and size of the image is specified in the 
				appropriate section below. </para>
				<tip>
					<para>The default images folder is maintained in the user preferences file. See
					the <link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
					User Preferences</emphasis></link>
					chapter for information on setting this value.</para>
				</tip>
				<para>When you load an image, the path to the image file is displayed in the
				text box below the "..." button in the image properties panel.
				The image below shows the background image properties
				panel after the background image used in the 
				<link linkend='gettingstarted'><emphasis role='underline'>Getting 
				Started</emphasis></link> tutorial has been
				loaded.</para>
				<figure xml:id="backgroundimageproperties3">
					<title>Background Image Properties With Sample Image Loaded</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/samplebackgroundimageproperties.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>There are
				two relative path specifiers: <filename class='directory'>$MyDocs$</filename> 
				is a reference to the current user's 
				<filename class='directory'>My Documents</filename> directory; 
				<filename class='directory'>$hamqslerFolder$</filename> is a references to the 
				<filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename> directory
				in the current user's <filename class='directory'>My Documents</filename> 
				directory. If the image file is located anywhere
				other than in <filename class='directory'>My Documents</filename>, 
				<filename class='directory'>hamqsler</filename>, 
				or a subdirectory of these directories, then
				the full path name is specified. The path in the image above specifies that 
				the image file is located at 
				<filename>...\My Documents\hamqsler\Samples\sample.jpg</filename>.</para>
			</section>
			<section xml:id='settingcolors'>
				<title>Setting Colors</title>
				<para>The color of text in text items as well as the color of text and lines
				in the Qsos Box may be changed. The current color of an item is shown in a button
				in the card item's properties panel. For example, the image below shows the
				text color label and button on the text item properties panel.</para>
				<figure xml:id="textcolor">
					<title>Text Color Label and Button</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/textcolor.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>In this case, the text in the text item is black as shown inside the
				button. Clicking on the button opens the color picker dialog which is shown
				in the following image. The image shows the color picker as it would be if
				you had clicked the text color button above. Note that the black color
				swatch in the Basic colors section is selected, matching the color in the
				text color button. If the previously set color does not exactly match
				one of the colors in the Basic color swatches, then the first color
				swatch is highlighted, even though that color does not match.</para>
				<figure xml:id="colorpicker2">
					<title>Color Picker Dialog</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/colorpicker.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>There are several ways to select a color:</para>
				<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
					<listitem>
						<para>Click on a color swatch in the Basic colors section. Note the
						ColorSolid swatch, and the settings of the Hue, Saturation and 
						Luminance text boxes, and the
						Red, Green, and Blue boxes. The displayed values match the selected
						color.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Click on a location in the color rainbow, then move the
						slider located to the right of the rainbow to adjust the 
						luminance of the selected color. Note that the
						Hue, Saturation, and Luminance values, as well as the Red, Green,
						and Blue values, change to match the color. The ColorSolid swatch
						also changes to match.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Enter the Hue, Saturation, and Luminance values directly. Valid
						values are from 0 to 240.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Enter the Red, Green, and Blue values directly. Valid values
						range from 0 to 255. You are probably much more familiar with this
						method of specifying a color than using hue, saturation, and
						luminance.</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				<para>Once you have chosen the color you want, click the OK button to select it.
				The color picker dialog will close, the color of the button will change to match
				the chosen color, and the corresponding card item property will change to 
				that color.</para>
				<tip>
					<para>In the color picker dialog, there is an "Add to Custom Colors" button.
					If you click on that button, the chosen color will be added to the Custom
					colors swatches. Custom colors are saved for display the next time that
					you open the color picker dialog.</para>
				</tip>
			</section>
			<section xml:id='settingdropdownboxvalues'>
				<title>Setting Dropdown Box Values</title>
				<para>In a dropdown box, the list of acceptable values is shown when you click
				on the dropdown box. There are several ways to select a value:</para>
				<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
					<listitem>
						<para>Click anywhere in the dropdown box to open it. Select the value
						you want by clicking on it. The dropdown list closes and the selected
						value is displayed in the box.
						If the list is long, it will not all be displayed in the dropdown.
						To scroll up the list, place the mouse cursor at the top of the
						dropdown; to scroll down the list, place the mouse cursor at the bottom
						of the dropdown. Alternatively, you may scroll using the mouse
						wheel.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Using the keyboard, tab until the dropdown box is selected. This is
						indicated by a dashed line around the text in the dropdown box. Use
						the up and down arrow keys, or the left and right arrow keys,
						to move to the previous and next values in
						the list.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Using the keyboard, tab until the dropdown box is selected. Press
						the keys matching the first few letters of the value you want to select.
						As you press the keys, the first item in the dropdown list that matches
						that set of keys is selected. Keep pressing keys until the value you
						want is selected.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Using the keyboard, tab until the dropdown box is selected.
						Press the first character of the value you want to select. The first
						value in the list that starts with that character is selected. Pressing
						the same key will select the second value that starts with that
						character. Keep pressing the key until the value you want is selected.
						Note: you must not pause between keypresses or the first value
						in the list will be selected again.</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</section>
			<section xml:id='settingcomboboxvalues'>
				<title>Setting Combobox Values</title>
				<para>A combobox is a combination of a dropdown box and a text box. A set
				of values is displayed in a dropdown box, and values not in the dropdown
				may be entered.</para>
				<para>Because a combobox is a dropdown box, all of the methods described in
				the section above may be used to select a predefined value. You may also
				enter a value as you would in a text box, using the keyboard.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Setting Background Image Properties</title>
			<para>The only property for a background image is the image file name. The method for
			setting this property is described in the
			<link linkend='imagefilename'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting an Image File 
			Name</emphasis></link> section, above.</para>
			<para>When you set the image file name for a background image, the image will be
			sized to completely cover the card; if the aspect ratio of the image is different from
			the aspect ratio of the card, then the image will extend either to the left and right
			of the card or the top and bottom of the card. You saw this in the
			<link linkend="gettingstarted"><emphasis role='underline'>Getting 
			Started</emphasis></link> tutorial.</para>
			<para>You may move and resize the image by following the instructions in the
			<link linkend='movingcarditem'><emphasis role='underline'>Moving and Resizing 
			Card Items</emphasis></link> section of this chapter.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Setting Secondary Image Properties</title>
			<para>The method for specifying the image file name for a secondary image is
			described in the 
			<link linkend='imagefilename'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting an Image File 
			Name</emphasis></link>
			section above. When the image is displayed for the first time, it is centered on the
			card, and the shorter of the width and height dimensions of the image is set to 1 inch
			or 25.4 mm. You may move and resize the image using the instructions in the
			<link linkend='movingcarditem'><emphasis role='underline'>Moving and Resizing 
			Card Items</emphasis></link> section in this chapter.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Setting Text Item Properties</title>
			<para>When a text item is selected, the text item properties panel is displayed
			in the card properties panel. The image below shows the text item
			properties panel when the callsign text item is selected.</para>
			<figure xml:id="textitemproperties2">
				<title>Text Item Properties Panel for Callsign Text Item</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/textitemproperties.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The font used to display the text item is selected using the font
			dropdown box. See 
			<link linkend='settingdropdownboxvalues'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting Dropdown
			Box Values</emphasis></link>, above for methods to select a font from this 
			dropdown box.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>Choose a font that is easy to read.
				In general, proportionally spaced fonts are easier to read than
				fixed-width fonts. Also, choose a standard serif or sans-serif font; do
				not use a script or abstract font. As you can see from the table below,
				Verdana, a proportionally spaced, sans-serif font, and Times New
				Roman, a proportionally spaced, serif font, are easy to read.
				Edwardian Script ITC, a script font, and Blackadder ITC, an abstract font, 
				are difficult to read.</para>
				<table frame='all'>
					<title>Font Examples</title>
					<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
						<colspec align='center'/>
						<colspec align='center'/>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<inlinemediaobject>
										<imageobject>
											<imagedata fileref="images/verdana.png" align="center" />
										</imageobject>
									</inlinemediaobject>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									<inlinemediaobject>
										<imageobject>
											<imagedata fileref="images/timesnewroman.png" align="center" />
										</imageobject>
									</inlinemediaobject>
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Verdana</entry>
								<entry>Times New Roman</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry></entry>
								<entry></entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<inlinemediaobject>
										<imageobject>
											<imagedata fileref="images/edwardianscriptitc.png" align="center" />
										</imageobject>
									</inlinemediaobject>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									<inlinemediaobject>
										<imageobject>
											<imagedata fileref="images/blackadderitc.png" align="center" />
										</imageobject>
									</inlinemediaobject>
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Edwardian Script ITC</entry>
								<entry>Blackadder ITC</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</tip>
			<tip>
				<para>Use only one or two font faces per card. You can distinguish different
				text items by position, font weight, font style, font size, or color.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>Checking and unchecking the Bold checkbox switches between bold and normal
			font weights.</para>
			<para>Checking and unchecking the Italic checkbox switches between italic and
			normal font styles.</para>
			<caution>
				<para>Not all font faces support the italic style. In such cases, the
				text remains displayed in the normal style.</para>
			</caution>
			<para>The font size (in points) may be set using the font size combobox. 
			You may either select
			a predefined value, or enter a different value. The value entered must be greater
			than 0; if 0 is entered, the value 1 is actually used. See 
			<link linkend='settingcomboboxvalues'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting Combobox 
			Values</emphasis></link> above
			for information on using this combobox.</para>
			<para>Click on the text color button to open the color picker dialog to select
			a color for the text. See 
			<link linkend='settingcolors'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
			Colors</emphasis></link>
			above for selecting a color using the color picker dialog.</para>
			<para>In the image above, the Text groupbox contains a static text box with the
			text "VA3HJ" and a Macros button. See the 
			<link linkend='macros'><emphasis role='underline'>Macros</emphasis></link>
			chapter for information on using macros.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>See 
				<link linkend='nonkeyboardchars'><emphasis role='underline'>Appendix C</emphasis></link>
				if you want to enter characters that are not available
				on your keyboard.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>The Check Boxes group box contains a number of properties related to
			the display of check boxes before and after the text in a text item.</para>
			<para>To place a checkbox before the text, check the Before Text checkbox. To
			place a checkbox after the text, check the After Text checkbox.</para>
			<para>To set the thickness of the checkboxes, adjust the Line Thickness
			slider. The value displayed is in hundredths of an inch.</para>
			<para>To change the size of the checkboxes, adjust the Check Box Ratio slider.
			The value that is displayed is the ratio of the height and and width of the checkboxes
			to the total height of the text item.</para>
		</section>
		<section xml:id='settingqsosboxproperties'>
			<title>Setting Qsos Box Properties</title>
			<para>The Qsos Box properties panel, shown in the image below, is displayed in the 
			card properties panel when the Qsos Box is selected.</para>
			<figure xml:id="qsosboxproperties2">
				<title>Qsos Box Properties Panel</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/qsosboxprops.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>The default confirming text, that is, the confirming text that is displayed
			if you have not changed it in user preferences, is "Confirming Two-Way QSOs With
			<emphasis>callsign</emphasis> via <emphasis>manager</emphasis>". The state of
			the Show Manager checkbox determines whether the text 
			"via <emphasis>manager</emphasis>" is printed on the card. If the checkbox is
			checked and the QSOs printed on the card contain a manager field, then the text
			is printed; if the checkbox is unchecked, then the text is not printed.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>The confirming text is stored in the user preferences file. See the
				<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User 
				Preferences</emphasis></link>
				chapter for information on changing this text.</para>
			</tip>
			<caution>
				<para>The confirming text is saved with the card file when the card is created.
				The only way to change this text is to change the confirming text item
				in user preferences, then create a new card.</para>
			</caution>
			<para>The Qsos Box may contain either a band or a frequency column. The column
			that is printed on the card is controlled by the Show Band Column and Show
			Freq Column radio buttons. Set the Show Band Column radio button to show a
			Band column, or set the Show Frequency Column radio button to show a Frequency
			column.</para>
			<para>If, when a QSO is loaded or input, it includes a frequency field and not
			a band field, a band field that corresponds to the frequency is added to the 
			QSO. If a band field is included in the QSO when loaded or input, but no
			frequency field is included and the Show Freq Column checkbox is checked,
			then when the card containing the QSO is printed, a frequency value based on
			the band field is substituted.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>The frequency value that is substituted is determined by values stored
				in the user preferences file. See the
				<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User
				Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter
				for information on changing the values that are substituted.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>The Qsos Box may contain an optional QSL column containing text such as
			"Pse" or "Tnx" for each QSO. Check the Show QSL Column checkbox to include the
			column; uncheck the checkbox to not include the column. The width of each
			column in the Qsos Box is adjusted based on the state of this checkbox.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>The QSL column header text and the text printed for each QSO is set
				in the user preferences file. See the 
				<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User 
				Preferences</emphasis></link> chapter
				for information on changing the text.</para>
			</tip>
			<caution>
				<para>The text values are saved in the card file when the card is created
				and are therefore fixed for the card. A new card must be created if you
				want to change the text.</para>
			</caution>
			<para>The Date Format dropdown box contains a selection of formats used to
			print the dates in the date column on the card. The setting also determines the
			header that is printed for the date column. Select the date format you want from
			the dropdown box. Methods for selecting a value are discussed in the
			<link linkend='settingdropdownboxvalues'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
			Dropdown Box Values</emphasis></link> section.</para>
			<para>The following date formats are available:</para>
			<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
				<listitem>
					<para>YYYY-MM-DD. This is one of the ISO 8601 date formats.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>DD-MMM-YY. A three character month value is substituted for "MMM"
					when the date is printed.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>DD-MM-YY.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<tip>
				<para>The header text that is printed or displayed in the date column is
				determined by the date format selected. The header text for each format
				may be set in the user preferences file. See the
				<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting User 
				Preferences</emphasis></link>
				chapter for more information.</para>
			</tip>
			<tip>
				<para>The default date format is also set in the user preferences file.
				See the <link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
				User Preferences</emphasis></link>
				chapter for information on how to set this default value.</para>
			</tip>
			<tip>
				<para>The three character month abreviations are saved in the user
				preferences file. See the 
				<link linkend='settinguserprefs'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
				User Preferences</emphasis></link>
				chapter for information on how to change these values.</para>
			</tip>
			<caution>
				<para>The header text for each date format is saved 
				in the card file when the card is created. The only way to change these
				values is to change them in user preferences and then create a new card.</para>
			</caution>
			<para>The value selected in the Max QSOs dropdown box determines the maximum
			number or QSOs that can be printed on a card. This is also the number of lines
			for QSOs that are displayed in design mode. The actual number of lines printed
			in the Qsos Box matches the number of QSOs being printed on the card. If
			no QSOs are being printed on the card, the QSOs Box that is printed contains
			an empty line for each of the maximum number of QSOs.</para>
			<para>Click the Line and Text Color button to change the color that the Qsos Box
			lines and text are printed in. This opens a Color Picker dialog to allow selection
			of a color. See the 
			<link linkend='settingcolors'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
			Colors</emphasis></link>
			section for information on how to select a color.</para>
			<para>Click the Callsign Color button to set the color that the callsign
			in the confirming text is printed in. This opens a Color Picker dialog to allow
			the selection of a color.</para>
			<para>Click the Manager Color button to set the color that the "via
			<emphasis>manager</emphasis>" text in the confirming text is printed in. This
			opens a Color Picker dialog to allow the selection of the color.</para>
			<para>The Font Size dropdown box contains a list of font sizes (in points) that
			the text in the Qsos Box can be printed in. Select a value using one of the
			methods described in the 
			<link linkend='settingdropdownboxvalues'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
			Dropdown Box Values</emphasis></link> section.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>As described in the 
				<link linkend='movingcarditem'><emphasis role='underline'>Moving and Resizing
				Card Items</emphasis></link> section in this chapter, the width of the 
				Qsos Box may be
				resized. The minimum width for the Qsos Box is determined by the width
				of the text displayed in each column. The width of the text is determined
				by the font size that the text is displayed or printed in. Select a smaller
				font size to reduce the minimum width for the Qsos Box.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>The selected value in the Font dropdown box determines the font face that
			the text in the Qsos Box is displayed or printed in. Select the font you want
			to use. The dropdown box contains all of the fonts located in the Fonts
			system directory that are registered on your computer.</para>
			<tip>
				<para>A card that uses too many different font faces looks busy and amaterish.
				Use only one or two font faces on your card. Use different font sizes,
				font weights, font styles, and colors for text items rather than different
				font faces to distinguish among the various pieces of information on the
				card.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>The Qsos Box background has two properties: color and opacity. Click the
			Background Color button to set the background color. This opens a Color Picker
			dialog that allows you to select a color. See the
			<link linkend='settingcolors'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
			Colors</emphasis></link> section, above, for
			information on how to select a color.</para>
			<para>Once the background color has been set, adjust the Background Opacity
			slider to set the opacity (reverse of transparency) of the Qsos Box. The lower
			the opacity value, the more any card items behind the text box show through.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Ideas For Handling Multiple Choices</title>
			<para>The following subsections discuss different ways that you can handle
			multiple items. For example, you may have multiple callsigns, operate from
			multiple QTHs, and may want to QSL a number of QSOs with the same station, some
			of which you have received QSL cards for and some for which you have not received
			QSL cards.</para>
			<section xml:id='multiplecallsigns'>
				<title>Handling Multiple Callsigns</title>
				<para>There are several ways that you can handle multiple callsigns:</para>
				<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
					<listitem>
						<para>Create a different card for each callsign.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Have a text item with a checkbox for each callsign. Use a pen
						to check the box for the appropriate callsign. You would have to
						select only those QSOS for one callsign to use this method, or 
						save your logs for each callsign in a different log file.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>For your callsign text item, use an AdifMacro to retrieve the
						STATION_CALLSIGN field from the QSOs. If your logging program does
						not log STATION_CALLSIGN, use the OPERATOR field instead. Finally,
						if the OPERATOR field is not logged, check for the OWNER_CALLSIGN
						field. Be sure to check the Separate Cards by ADIF Field checkbox
						for the macro. See the 
						<link linkend='macros'><emphasis role='underline'>Macros</emphasis></link>
						chapter for information on the AdifMacro.</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</section>
			<section xml:id='multipleqths'>
				<title>Handling Multiple QTHs</title>
				<para>There are also several ways to handle multiple QTHs:</para>
				<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
					<listitem>
						<para>Create a different card for each QTH. You would want to use
						this method if you use different images for each QTH.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Have a text item with a checkbox for each QTH. Use a pen
						to check the appropriate QTH. You would have to select only those
						QSOs for one QTH to use this method.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>If your logging program uses an application specific
						field to specify unique QTHs that you operate from, use an
						AdifMacro in a text item to specify the QTH. Check the Separate
						Cards by ADIF Field checkbox for the macro. See the
						<link linkend='macros'><emphasis role='underline'>Macros</emphasis></link>
						chapter for information on the AdifMacro.</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</section>
			<section xml:id='pseqsltnx'>
				<title>Please QSL Thanks</title>
				<para>Every QSL card should contain either a request for a QSL card from 
				the other station, or a thanks for the card that the other station sent you. 
				<literal>HamQSLer</literal> provides a number of ways of accomplishing this:</para>
				<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
					<listitem>
						<para>If you only send QSL cards in response to a received card, then 
						<link linkend='addingtextitems'>add a text item</link> containing the 
						text "Thanks QSL" somewhere on the card.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><link linkend='addingtextitems'>Add a text item</link> 
						containing the text "Please QSL Thanks" or "Pse QSL Tnx" on the card 
						and use a pen to strike out the "Please" or "Thanks" as 
						appropriate.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para><link linkend='addingtextitems'>Add a text item</link>
						containing the text "Please QSL Thanks" or "Pse QSL Tnx" with a 
						checkbox at each end. Use a pen to check the box that is 
						appropriate.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>An alternative to the item above is to add two text items
						to the card with a checkbox before each text item. The text for the
						two text items would be "Pse QSL" and "Tnx QSL" or similar. Use a
						pen to check the appropriate checkbox.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>What if you are QSLing a number of QSOs, some that you received a
						QSL card for, and some that you did not receive a QSL card for? An
						optional QSL column may be added to the Qsos Box with "Pse" or "Tnx"
						printed as appropriate for each QSO. See
						<link linkend='settingqsosboxproperties'><emphasis role='underline'>Setting 
						Qsos Box Properties</emphasis></link> for more information.</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Two-Sided Cards</title>
		<para><literal>HamQSLer</literal> does not directly support the design and printing 
		of two-sided cards.
		You could use the following method to create a two-sided card:</para>
		<orderedlist spacing='compact'>
			<listitem>
				<para>Design a QSL card that will serve as the front of your card. Include
				one or more images, your callsign, and possibly a greeting or your city,
				etc. Delete other text and the Qsos Box from the card so that they will not
				be printed.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Design another card that will serve as the back of your card. Include
				additional images if you wish, your callsign, all other text, and the
				Qsos Box.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>When you print the cards, first print the front of the cards, then
				reload the cardstock in your printer so that the backside can be printed. 
				Print the back of the card.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
</chapter>
